>> let's see everybody is here
now.
>> good afternoon everyone.
Welcome to the MAY 20th, 2025
regular meeting of the san
francisco board of supervisors.
>> MADAM Clerk, will you please
call the roll?
Thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
Supervisor chan chen present
supervisor chen chen present
supervisor dorsey dorsey
present supervisor engardio
and engardio present supervisor
fielder fielder present
supervisor mahmood mahmood
present supervisor randleman
PRESIDENT Randleman present
supervisor melgar melgar
present supervisor her sadr
sadr present supervisor cheryl
cheryl not present
and supervisor and supervisor
walton walton present MR.
PRESIDENT you have a quorum.
>> thank you MADAM Clerk the
san francisco board of
supervisors acknowledges that
we are in the unceded ancestral
homeland of the romita colony
who are the original
inhabitants of the san
francisco peninsula as the
indigenous stewards of this
land and in accordance with
their traditions the
ramakrishna loni have never
ceded lost nor forgotten their
responsible parties as the
caretakers of this place as
well as for all peoples who
reside in their traditional
territory as guests we
recognize that we benefit from
living and working on their
traditional homeland.
we wish to pay our respects by
acknowledging the ancestors,
elders and relatives of the
ramakrishna aloni community
and by affirming their
sovereign rights as first
peoples.
Colleagues, will you join me
in reciting the pledge of
allegiance?
>> I pledge allegiance to the
flag of the united states
and to the republic for which
it stands one nation under GOD,
indivisible with liberty.
>> on behalf of the board I
want to acknowledge the staff
at S.F. Gov tv today
particularly james kawana.
They record each of our
meetings and make the
transcripts available to the
public online.
>> MADAM Clerk, do you have any
communications?
Yes I do.
Thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
The san francisco board of
supervisors welcomes attendees
who are here in person today at
this meeting.
Here in the board's legislative
chamber within city hall on the
second floor in room 250.
You MAY also watch the
proceeding on S.F. Govee tv's
channel 26 or view the live
stream at ww dot S.F. Gov
tv.Org if you have public
comment you'd like to submit
in writing use the email
address box at S.F. Gov dot org
or via the U.S. Postal service.
Address your envelope to the
san francisco board of
supervisors the number one
doctor carleton capital b
period good lit place city hall
room 244 san francisco,
california 94102 if you need to
make a reasonable accommodation
request under the americans
with disability act or if you
need language assistance
contact the clerk's office at
least two business days
in advance by calling
(415) 554-5184.
Thank you MR. PRESIDENT.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Let's go to the approval of our
meeting minutes APRIL 15th,
2025 board meeting minutes.
>> all right.
I don't see anyone on the
roster with changes.
Seeing none.
Can I have a motion to approve
the minutes as presented moved
by walton.
Can I have a second seconded by
chan.
>> and MADAM Clerk, will you
please call the roll on the
minutes as presented supervisor
mahmud mahmood I supervisor
randleman.
All right randleman I
supervisor melgar melgar I
supervisor sutter sauder I
supervisor cheryl cheryl I
supervisor walton walton I
supervisor chin chin I
supervisor dorsey dorsey I
supervisor and gaudio
and gaudio I and supervisor
fielder fielder either are
lebanese without objection the
minutes will be be will be
approved after public comment
as presented MADAM Clerk let's
go to new business please call
items one through three items
one through three comprise
three go or general obligation
bonds for a health safety
and vibrant san francisco.
I don't want is the ordinance
to appropriate 100 194 million
of geo bond proceeds from
series 2025 f to the department
of public health, public works
and the municipal
transportation agency for
acquisition and improvement of
real property for health care,
nursing and mental health
facilities transportation
pedestrian streets safety
related capital improvements,
streetscape enhancements
and other public space
improvements and to place these
funds on controllers reserve
pending receipt of bond
proceeds in fiscal year 2024
through 25 for item two.
This is a resolution to provide
for the issuance of a $390
million gio bond from series
2024 to authorize the issuance
and sale of said bonds to
provide for the levy of a tax
to pay the principal
and interest thereof to provide
for the appointment of
depositories and other agents
for said bonds to provide for
the establishment of accounts
related there to and to adopt
the appropriate findings.
>> and for item three this is a
resolution to authorize the
issuance and sale of a $194
million bond of one or more
series of citgo bonds for
series 2024 series 2025 f on a
tax exempt or taxable basis to
prescribed the form and terms
of such bonds and any
subsidiary designation to
provide for the appointment of
depositories and other agents
to provide for the
establishment of accounts or
subaccounts to authorize the
sale of such bonds by
competitive or negotiated sale
or private placement to approve
the forms of various official
forms, contract statements
and certificate certificates
and notices and to ratify
certain actions previously
taken as defined herein and to
grant general authority to city
officials to take the necessary
actions in connection with the
authorization at issuance sale
and delivery of the bonds.
>> MADAM Clerk, please call the
roll on items one through
three.
Supervisor mahmood mahmood I
supervisor randleman.
All right gentlemen, I'm
supervisor melgar melgar.
I'm supervisor sadr sadr I
supervisor cheryl cheryl I
supervisor walton walton I
supervisor chan chin I
supervisor chin chin I
supervisor dorsey dorsey I
supervisor engardio
and engardio I and supervisor
fielder fielder I.
There are 11 eyes without
objection the ordinance is
passed on first reading and the
resolutions are adopted MADAM
Clerk please call item for item
for this ordinance the
appropriate 250,000 from
general city responsibility
and appropriates 250,000 to the
children, youth and families to
support the district ten safety
plan including services at the
hope safe sites violence
prevention events safe passages
,response to schools and as
needed support to our youth
and residents most impacted by
violence in fiscal year 2024
through 2025 we can take this
item same house, same call.
>> without objection the
ordinance is passed on first
reading MADAM Clerk please call
item five item five this is an
ordinance to amend the
administrative code to allow
city departments to enter into
and amend agreements for
accelerated acquisition of fire
apparatus without complying
with solicitation requirements
that would otherwise apply
and without complying with
provisions in the municipal
code that impose obligations on
contracting parties as a
condition of contracting with
the city.
>> let's take this item same
house, same call.
>> without objection the
ordinance is passed on first
reading MADAM Clerk please call
item six item six resolution to
retroactively authorize the
department of emergency
management to accept and expend
an approximate 2.7 million
in regional catastrophic
preparedness grant funds for
the duration of OCTOBER 1st
2020 for through SEPTEMBER 30th
2027 and will take this same
house same call.
>> without objection this
resolution is adopted.
MADAM Clerk, please call item
seven and eight together.
>> item seven and eight are two
resolutions that pertain to
grant agreements for food
assistance program.
Item seven approves an
agreement between the human
services agency and the glide
foundation for the free meals
program duration JULY 1st, 2025
through JUNE 30th 2029 for an
approximate amount of 14.1
million.
And item eight approves the
agreement between the
department of disability
and aging services and the san
francisco marin food bank for
the provision of the food
assistance program duration
JULY 1st, 2025 through JUNE
30th 2029 and an approximate
amount of 12.6 million.
>> we can take these items same
house, same call without
objection the resolutions are
adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk, please call
item nine.
>> item nine this is a
resolution to approve
and authorize the sale of an
approximate 46,000 square foot
portion of the san francisco
public utilities commission's
partial 21.
Located in south san francisco
for 132,000 to the city of san
francisco and to adopt the
appropriate findings.
>> again same house, same call
without objection the
resolutions adopted.
MADAM Clerk, please call item
ten.
>> item ten.
This is a resolution to approve
and authorize the terms
and conditions and to authorize
the director of property and or
the general manager of the san
francisco public utilities
commission to execute a
purchase and sale agreement
and easement deeds with bay
area rapid transit district for
the acquisition of
approximately 14,000 square
foot permanent access easement
and an approximate 2000 square
foot temporary construction
easement for 306,000 on
and across portion portions of
san mateo county's assessor's
parcel number 093-330-120
and to adopt the appropriate
findings and same house
and call without objection this
resolution is adopted.
MADAM Clerk please call items
11 and 12 together items 11
and 12 are two items that
pertain to the 160 free lawn
housing project.
>> item 11 is a resolution to
approve and authorize the
director of property and the
mayor's office of housing
and community development to
enter into a ground lease for
real property owned by the city
located at 160 freeland street
with 160 free lawn housing
partners lp for 75 year lease
term and 120 for lease 124 year
option to extend with an annual
base rent of 15,000 to
construct a 100% affordable 84
unit multi rental housing
development affordable to low
income households plus one
manager's unit to include 22
local operating subsidy program
units reserved for formerly
homeless households and five
units for referrals from the
city's plus housing list and to
approve and authorize an
amended and restated loan
agreement in the amount of 22.5
million for a 57 year minimum
loan term and to adopt the
appropriate findings for item
12.
This is a resolution to
authorize the execution
and delivery of multifamily
housing revenue notes in one or
more series for 76 million to
provide financing to construct
an 85 unit multifamily rental
housing project located at 160
freeland street known as 160
freeland and to authorize the
collection of certain fees to
approve the execution
and delivery of federally tax
exempt residential mortgage
revenue notes by the city in an
aggregate principal amount not
to exceed 48.9 million to
approve modifications, changes
and additions to the document
to ratify and approve actions
heretofore taken in connection
with the back to back loans,
the notes and the project
and we can take these same
house same call without
objection these resolutions are
adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk please call item
13.
Item 13 is a resolution to
authorize the treasure island
development authority to
execute a grant application
under the department of housing
and community development
and the california strategic
growth council.
Affordable housing
and sustainable communities
program as a joint applicant
with I.S. 4.3 family housing lp
for a not to exceed amount of
50 million and to adopt the
appropriate findings.
>> same house, same call.
Without objection this
resolution is adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk, please call
item 14.
>> item 14 was referred without
recommendation from the budget
and finance committee.
Item 14 is a resolution to
retroactively authorize the
human rights commission to
execute a grant amendment
between the city and county
and the lavender youth
recreation board
and information center for a
program for the youth service.
Youth services and research on
the transgender and gender
nonconforming community to
extend the grant term through
DECEMBER 31st 2023 for a
contract amount of 300,000.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Chair chan thank you present
amendment colleagues these two
items as you can see really
following item 14 is item 15.
>> both came out of the budget
committee without
recommendation.
These two items actually I know
we have yet to call item 15 but
I just want to explain that
they have something in common.
>> both organizations provide
very critical services so I
think the city ought to invest
in and continue to invest in it
.
And yet in this case item 14 is
a retroactive payments that we
have to pay back to lyric
because we have only verbally
authorizing the spending
and services without really
evaluating the contract itself
and getting a appropriate
allocation of funds
and approval before we move
forward with the service.
>> so now we have to
retroactively providing the
funding to this organization.
And then the second piece is
again the item 15 that's going
to cost shortly also what our
recommendation is because they
the organization has been doing
really critical services but
have challenges
and difficulties really making
sure that they are in good
standing as an organization.
The way I see it is that the
city itself actually has a
responsibility to make sure
that our community partners
when we trust them and and
in partnership going to
contract and contract agreement
with our community partners we
ought to make sure that we
provide resources
and regulations
and explanations and training
to our community partners when
they deliver these services
they can deliver with
confidence but also meet the
standards.
And I think that both items
coming out with our
recommendation is that is that
the city is falling short
and in in our partnership with
this organization both
in supportive of them so that
they can move forward
and making sure that they are
either paid in whole or that
their organization is in good
standing so that we can
collectively and collaborate to
fully provide services
ultimately to our constituents
to to the community and to san
franciscans is really, really
should be the goal.
>> I hope that these two
contract before you today that
one is expiring and that it
will go go to rfp and then the
other one will be continuing
before us.
I hope to have your support
and that you will vote for both
of them but that does not mean
that when they do come back we
do not ask questions which we
will.
So I just wanted to alert for
you to to recognize that we
ought to continue to invest
in these services.
But I think we need to continue
to ask questions.
Thank you.
>> well, thank you chair chan
and I apologize.
I probably should have asked
our clerk to to call item 15 as
well with regard to 14.
I want to thank the committee
for its work from my
perspective as the sponsor of
the legislation I, I did think
that it was important that we
pay lyric for services
delivered with the
understanding that they were
being asked to do this by the
city and I think it is
important that we that we pass
that but I want to thank the
committee for its for its work
on this and its thought
and your thoughtfulness.
>> all right.
>> so on 14 unless there
objections I think we can take
this same house, same call
and the resolution is adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk, please call
item 15.
>> item 15 this is a resolution
to approve the fifth amendment
to the agreement between the
department of public health
and the bayview hunters point
foundation to provide mental
health and substance abuse
services to provide an 18 month
extension for a total duration
of JULY 1st 2018 through
DECEMBER 31st, 2026 and to
increase the amount by
approximately 1.27 million for
a total amount of 18 million.
>> thank you MADAM Clerk.
And again I think we can take
this item.
Same house, same call without
objection this resolution is
adopted.
>> and MADAM Clerk, can you
please call item 16 and 17
together?
>> item 16 and 17 are two
resolutions that determine if
two person to person premise to
premise transfers of a liquor
license will serve the public
convenience or necessity of the
city.
Item 16 determines that a time
21 off sale general beer wine
and distilled spirits liquor
license to alcohol super
mercato corp doing business as
el chavo super mercado located
at 15 ocean avenue will serve
the public convenience item 17
determines the type 20 of sale
general beer and wine liquor
license to casa guadalupe
supermarket two located at 3400
cesar chavez street will serve
the public convenience and to
request that the california
department of alcoholic
beverage control impose
conditions on the issuance of
each license.
>> and again we can take these
items same house, same call
without objection these
resolutions are adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk, please call
adam 18 item 18 this is a
motion to approve the mayor's
nomination for the appointment
of megan thurlow to the public
utilities commission term
ending AUGUST 1st, 2028.
>> same house, same call.
Without objection this this
motion is approved.
>> and then MADAM Clerk, please
call item 19.
Item 19.
This is a motion to approve the
mayor's nomination and for the
appointment of rebecca saroyan
to the board of appeals term
ending JULY 1st, 2028 and again
same house, same call.
Without objection this motion
is adopted.
Is approved and why don't we go
to our committee reports items
30 through 33 were considered
by the government audit
and oversight committee at a
regular meeting on thursday MAY
15th and were forwarded as
committee reports item 30 this
is an ordinance to authorize a
settlement with pacific gas
and electric company in federal
energy regulate regulatory
commission docket a numbers e r
2028 78 or 22 619 e r 22 620
and tex 20 1-4000.
These matters involve disputes
over the terms of japanese
wholesale distribution tariff
the proposed settlement
requires p, g and e to provide
secondary voltage service to
customers served by the public
utilities commission for ten
years.
>> MR. PRESIDENT, did you say
31 as well?
>> yeah.
Go ahead and call 31.
Item 31 this is an ordinance to
authorize settlement of the
lawsuit filed by arthur frazier
against the city for
approximately 111,000.
This lawsuit involves alleged
personal injury from a trip
and fall over a utility box on
a city sidewalk.
>> all right.
Let's take these same house,
same call.
>> without objection, these
ordinances are passed on first
reading MADAM Clerk, please
call item 32.
>> item 32 this is a resolution
to authorize the mayor the
mayor's chief of staff, the
chief of public safety.
The assistant chief of public
safety, a policy advisor
and the chief of the fire
department to solicit donations
from various private entities
and organizations to support
the procurement of fire
apparatus for six months from
the effective date of this
resolution notwithstanding the
behest of payment ordinance.
>> same house, same call
without objection, this
resolution is adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk, please call
item 33.
>> item 33 this is a resolution
to declare the intention of the
board of supervisors to renew a
property based business
improvement district known as
the dogpatch and northwest
potrero hill green benefit
district and to levy a
multi-year assessment on all
parcels in the district to
approve the management district
plan and engineer's report
and the proposed boundaries map
for the district to order
and set the time and place for
a public hearing of the board
of supervisors to convene a
committee of the whole on JULY
22nd 2025 at 3 P.M. To approve
the form of the notice of
public hearing and assessment
ballot proceeding
and assessment ballot to direct
environmental findings and to
direct the clerk of the board
to provide notice of the public
hearing and balloting as
required by law.
Okay and we'll take that item
same house, same call without
objection the resolution is
adopted at and MADAM Clerk, I
think that takes us to roll
call supervisor mahmood your
first to introduce new business
submit.
>> thank you PRESIDENT
Randleman all rights.
>> I have a couple of things.
First are as part of our
updates on outside boards I
want to report on what's going
on with the portal project from
the jpa in MARCH the mtc
commission unanimously advanced
the portal project to mtc's
topmost level of regional
priority and its map framework.
That action will align our
local advocacy with the
regional efforts to complete
the project's funding plan over
the next two years.
And earlier this month the gpa
board unanimously approved
moving forward with the next
step in the procurement process
to select the progressive
design build contractor for the
portal.
With this approval, tgp staff
are preparing to release the
request for proposals to the
shortlist of teams that were
pre-qualified under the
preceding request for
qualifications process.
Next year tgp plans to award
the contract for the selected
progressive design build team
to initiate the preconstruction
phase of design development
and then also this month the
tgp board reviewed the agency's
draft budget for the coming
fiscal year in anticipation of
approval by the board next
month.
I also have an in memoriam
today for alan wayne martinez
who died on APRIL 20th at the
age of 70.
Alan was born on JULY first,
1955 in santa maria.
>> a graduate of the university
of california berkeley college
of environmental design.
In 1977 alan worked as a
licensed architect for four
decades designing spaces that
connected contemporary forms
with historical narratives.
He served on the historic
preservation advisory board
historic preservation
commission and the store
preservation fund committee
and was instrumental
in safeguarding landmarks
and cultural sites.
Among his achievements he
coauthored with his fellow
commissioner diane masuda a
resolution to adopt social
heritage resources as part of
the planning department's
contact statements an important
step in recognizing the
cultural layers of urban
spaces.
He was also a coauthor of the
san francisco citywide pan
latino context statement
and was deeply involved in the
landmarking of the carnival
and charter murals with the
later honoring the late popular
radio host yeah, a late popular
radio host and deejay who
passed away in 2013.
Efforts that highlighted the
vibrancy and significance of
the city's latino cultural
contributions.
>> alan built a network of
friends who shared his
intellectual passions.
Among them were rebecca solnit,
whose literary explorations of
place and identity resonated
with alan's architectural
philosophy.
And professor robert cherney,
whose academic insights on
history and politics
complemented alan's thoughts on
preservation.
His best friend ed kindred
spirit was his closest
confidant accompanying him
in journeys both literal
and philosophical where the two
often delved into profound
discussions about humanity, art
and the evolving narratives of
urban spaces.
Alan martinez was not only a
dedicated professional he was a
compassionate individual with a
deep love for history
and humanity.
His ability to conceptualize
ideas, challenge conventions
and provoke thought made him a
unique force in san francisco's
architectural and intellectual
worlds.
He was a champion of history, a
steward of preservation and a
tireless advocate for the
stories that buildings
and landscapes could tell.
He's survived by his older
brother richard martinez.
He also leaves behind a circle
of cherished friends
and colleagues from the san
francisco preservation
community.
The san francisco latino
historical society, S.F.
Heritage, the S.F. Preservation
commission and the lgbtq
friends of 1800.
Rest in peace and power alan
martinez.
MAY your memory be a blessing.
The rest I submit and I believe
that that brings us to our 230
special order.
>> adam clark yes, this is the
special order a 230 which is
the recognition of
commendations for meritorious
service to the city and county
of san francisco.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
A number of supervisors today
are doing commendations
in recognition of ap
and heritage month and I
thought it might be appropriate
since we have the founder of
the apa heritage foundation
and annual organizer of our apa
heritage events in MAY to give
claudine chang the opportunity
to say hi and offer a few a few
words along with one of her
loyal troop thomas lee
representing the others.
>> good afternoon and happy
aapi month again everyone I
know I've seen many of you
during the last 2 or 3 weeks at
events.
>> it is our 20 first year.
>> it's quite amazing to think
of how sometimes you think
about a baby going to school
and high school and college
and now it's almost and that
this and every year we think
about we really challenge
ourselves in that this should
not be more of the same because
that can happen when things
happen year after year.
But the committee really got
together and every year we
challenge ourselves to see what
can we do different this year,
how we can be energized more
people.
And this year the theme as many
of you know is energizing the
next generation.
>> and we are very excited
because because we look back
and just the last 2 or 3 weeks
there were a couple of events
that really stood out in my
mind and maybe thomas can share
his one is opportunity because
of the theme energizing the
next generation to actually
work with a group of youth
advisors.
I mean these are folks from 12
year old to 24 year old.
A couple of them are active
members of the san francisco
youth commission and it's
amazing what they do.
And because of their effort
that we were able to launch
this year for the first year,
the aapi youth changemaker
awards for those of you who are
at the ceremony that there was
a ceremony were able to see the
two amazing you know youth one
is 12 year oh the other 15
and what they were able to
accomplish in in that very
young age it's really inspiring
.
>> fast forward to this past
weekend.
It was very energizing and I
just want to say that of all
this is that this was really
one two of the most touching
moments this past weekend.
Just wanted to share with you.
One is being there to with the
pacific islanders cultural with
the unfurling of the pacific
islander cultural district I
want to share thanks supervisor
walton for having worked with
the pacific islanders community
for the last two or 3 or 4
years making sure that they it
happened they really were
really grateful to you and to
all the supervisors who have
put it disrupt the resolution
and making sure that this
happened.
>> it means so much to the
people of pacific islanders who
feel that their voices have not
been heard in the past.
Now they feel that they can
finally see a home where they
belong and it is this is very
touching and I want to thank
supervisors liang chiang for
being there and to be part of
the parade because people want
to be part of the city and and
aapi heritage celebration is
not just about at hope's
theater or at about a city hall
we really want to expand this
so that everyone every district
there is some celebration
and that's what we are excited
about and and of course also
this weekend to see the closing
of our events chow fun again
also supersized by its own chan
I mean it's just amazing to see
because we also want to look
for continue to look for
opportunity to jointly
celebrate the whole month of
MAY is filled with reasons to
MISS So many reasons to
celebrate a small business week
so as a result of our co-chair
l perez everett you know
childfund is now in its third
year and this is greatly
expanded within district ten
and district 11 and we have
actually gotten quite a few
merchants that came up and say
hey, we want to be part of that
next year.
I mean that is why we do it
because we want to continue to
feel that there's engagement
and that people feel
enthusiastic that all this
means something to so many
people and your support
and your participation means a
lot.
>> and and on that note, I want
to invite all of you tomorrow
night after all your meetings
to come to the boom boom room.
Yeah, the boom boom room
in japantown where the aapi
heritage celebration committee
will be celebrating with its
fellow culture with on the
celebration of the jewish
jewish american month.
So that would be a lot of fun.
>> so hope you can join us.
And here is our celebration
co-chair tom asli thomas has
really been tirelessly working
on this with the community for
over ten years and he is he is
the brain and the mind behind
every piece of publicity
materials that you have seen
out there.
They are the creation of thomas
and we were so grateful because
we are really just a group of
volunteers that shared the
vision that we want to amplify
the month.
>> so thomas yeah, I think
every year at this celebration
gets bigger and bigger and one
of my highlights this year was
fest.
There was a brand new
documentary by our own john
ozaki from japantown who is the
executive director of js who I
see on top of that he created a
film documenting youth of
rising a api, a nonprofit youth
group that's speaking up to
integrate aapi history culture
in lessons plans all across the
united states and it's so
empowering to see young voices
speaking at town halls,
speaking up water education,
fighting for their history,
integrate it into the lesson
lesson plans because that is
something that I wanted to see
in my lesson plans growing up
in san francisco.
But it's so beautiful to see
young voices speaking up loud
and proud so happy aapi
heritage month everyone thank
you claudine and thomas and to
all of the other folks on the
organizing committee who do so
much to make ap heritage month
great and san francisco.
>> all right.
So we have lots of supervisors
understandably with with
commendations today and just to
give folks a heads up on how
this is going to work, we're
going to start with our with
our api supervisors and that's
going to and because of our
roll call order that's going to
start with supervisor mahmood
and then we have supervisor
chan and chan.
Supervisor fielder has has an
honoree who needs to leave
quickly so I hope folks won't
mind if she skips in next then
we'll get supervisor dorsey
and then we'll go back to our
regular order walton
and engardio and then as this
traditional date will go last
so we will start with d five
supervisor mahmood thank you
colleagues and I wanted to
thank again supervisor chen
and chen for co-sponsoring our
luncheon earlier today
and thanks for all who attended
today.
>> I want to colleagues have
the deep honor of recognizing a
woman whose impact on civic
life in san francisco has been
nothing short of generational.
>> we are here to celebrate the
work and legacy of carol ito.
>> carol, do you want to
upstage carol is a lifelong
advocate, organizer and mentor
who has quietly and powerfully
shaped public service, woman's
leadership and neighborhood
empowerment for more than four
decades as one of the original
founders of the pacific asian
american woman bay area
coalition, carol has built an
enduring platform to uplift
and amplify asian-american
and pacific islander women.
And throughout her career she's
shown us that quiet leadership
can move mountains.
>> when I first ask around
about carol's work, I expected
to hear about her advocacy
and organizing what I didn't
expect though I should have was
how personal her impact has
been.
Time and again I heard the same
sentiment.
She's the one we turn to when
we need clarity.
She never asks for the
spotlight but she's always the
one getting things done.
And she's been a mentor to me.
Mary jang MAY have captured it
best when she said whether
carol realizes it or not, she
has been a mentor to many of
the leaders we see today.
>> her advice is always spot on
and comes from a vast reserve
of selflessness and willingness
to serve the public good.
She is relentless when she is
focused and that is why so many
of us rely on her to this day.
>> carol lee's not with volume
but with vision and that is a
rare and irreplaceable kind of
leadership that leadership
began around the kitchen table
.
>> that's where she and six
other visionary woman alice
below adrian cheng kwang carol
jan lee pearl louie cheryl
shirley wang and cathy n
gathered in the wake of title
nine to ask a crucial question
what would real equity look
like for asian and pacific
islander women?
From that question pay wbc was
born.
>> it became one of the first
spaces in the nation for aapi
woman to organize, lead
and influence public policy
rooted in the understanding
that their experiences were
distinct and their voices long
overdue to be heard.
This was more than organizing
it was movement building
grounded in cultural fluency
and a deep belief in the power
of community.
Carol has touched so much more
on her free time.
She also served as airport
commissioner, three term
PRESIDENT Of the san francisco
commission on the status of
women board of trustees for
saint francis memorial hospital
and co-chaired the first woman
summit of course no recognition
of carol would be complete
without highlighting her faith
while commitment to japantown.
One of san francisco's most
historic and culturally
culturally rich neighborhoods,
carol, has long worked to make
sure japantown is never
forgotten.
Whether it's city hall
in sacramento or in washington,
D.C., rick hashimoto, PRESIDENT
Of the japantown merchant
association, shared.
Carol always makes sure that
japantown is not forgotten with
our elected leaders
and departments.
She ensures that japantown
continues to remain in the
forefront on local, state
and federal government.
>> during the covid epidemic
when small businesses were
struggling to survive, carol
was on the front lines
advocating strategize
and making sure relief reached
those who needed it most.
>> she supported cultural
festivals and events for over
50 years and she's worked to
preserve kim and gwynn a vital
community institution where
children continue to learn the
japanese language and heritage
.
>> her advocacy in japantown
isn't episodic it's consistent,
unwavering and deeply rooted
in love for a place, a people
and for all that endures.
Carol is what we in district
five call a pillar someone
whose work is not always loud
but is foundational.
She's not only shaped policy
and preserved cultural memory
but people.
Steve nicastro, our fire
commissioner reminds us carol
has always encouraged
leadership development
and civic engagement especially
for aapi woman.
She's politically savvy, deeply
connected to neighborhoods
and she gets things done.
Carol's work through her
nonprofit work and beyond has
inspired hundreds of women to
step into civic life, advocate
for their communities and lead
with both clarity
and compassion.
She's a connector, a coach, a
conscience and above all a
public servant.
His impact speaks loudly
through our community.
So colleagues, please join me
in recognizing carol ito for
her lifelong dedication for the
api community and for her
unwavering advocacy
in japantown, for her
mentorship of generations of
leaders and for building the
civic and cultural architecture
of a more just and inclusive
san francisco.
Carol thank you for all you've
done to uplift, strengthen
and brighten the joy in our
community.
>> thank you, supervisor bilal
thank you.
Supervisor PRESIDENT Mandell
men and the board of
supervisors.
>> I first want to start I you
know supervisor here mahmood.
I just have to say you've
already in the first five
months made a tremendous
difference in district five
and for japantown and for the
tenderloin which is of course
the spotlight of our public
safety concerns in this city
and for change.
If the tenderloin changes, san
francisco image will change
and that is happening because
of your leadership and your
deep commitment.
I attended your first that I
festival and it was so touched
by all the children out on the
street enjoying the petting zoo
,the jumping house, you know,
and I used to be on saint
francis hospital board
and people used to come to me.
This was 25 years ago that we
have children here that need
care.
We have families that need
proper schools and you are one
of the first to really address
this and I saw that with the
muslim families coming out to
support that festival and I
hope that other of like the
vietnamese community will come
out next year.
There are many children
and latins, spanish speaking
families there.
So I really have to commend the
early work you've already
accomplished to bring
communities together and also
for your recognition to be
proactive in japantown.
>> I think most of the
leadership in japantown have
experienced reactive response.
You've been very proactive
almost to the point where
you're so people MAY not know
his sense of humor.
>> he attended our city really
year's festival to new years
ago in 2024 and he was on the
stage and nobody introduced him
but it was the moat and the
annual moki pound ceremony
which is for good luck for the
new year where you pound mochi
and there was bilal up on the
stage pounding mochi with all
these people he didn't know
with council general and other
leaders mostly men.
>> and so I have to say you
really a good sport and you
just got right in there and I
really appreciate it.
>> but I want to sort of focus
back and hopefully I'm not I
know some people have to leave
early.
>> I really commend this board
for spending part of today
acknowledging asian heritage
month.
And I have to commend my good
friend claudine chang who I
want to repeat when on MAY 1st
at the heritage event at her
theater she said well you must
double down this year and in
your term because of what's
going on in our national
picture of things.
>> and that sentence sisqo is
not shying away from dti.
You know diversity equity
and inclusion has to be led
forward with your strength
and leadership and I appreciate
your spending part of your
meeting today to emphasize the
leadership's and the
contributions of our community
and also I think the jewish
heritage month, you know,
coming together in cooperation
with the asian heritage month
is really important as well.
>> I just want to remind people
and I don't want to be
disrespectful but 40 years ago
maybe half of you were just
being born.
I was trying to figure out how
old about a third of the new
supervisors were and you know
are women organizations started
in 1980 right after title nine
was passed in 1972.
And I was heartened because I
did an interview on friday
about asian heritage month.
And if it wasn't for title nine
we would not have the warriors
values team in our city today.
When I was in high school
in the 60s we only did track
and field.
>> it was because of the
japanese community
in sacramento that some of us
girls got to play competitive
basketball back then.
>> okay.
So title nine allowed women to
play soccer to play tennis, to
play basketball.
>> and now we're seeing the
fruits of their effort
and their skill sets.
>> and I'm so proud that we
have a japanese-american head
coach here.
>> I mean who would have known
natalie nagasaki would be
leading our team here?
But it's really a lot of
excitement because we're seeing
women of color be more visible.
>> and I think also I just want
to speak briefly and I don't
want to be preachy about this.
My foundation doing work in the
asian women's community from
1980 to 89 helped me get a
point in my art agnus I was
invited to join the first
reconstituted commission on the
status women.
>> I know all of you are aware
the troubles that we've had
this last year.
I hope that the board will
support the current commission
on the status of women
proposition e task force is
full fledged going on is five
months.
Most people in this chamber
don't know that people are
reviewing there are five people
on that task force reviewing
all the commissions whether
we're going to exist or not.
>> and whether the mayor is
going to get more power or
there's going to be balance of
power between your body.
>> the chief administrative
officer and the mayor.
>> so there's a lot of thoughts
being shared.
>> and I just invite everybody
to be involved because the
commission on sat us women
in 19 in the 90 and nothing was
quantified lately when I was on
that commission there were
seven us appointed.
>> we were the first group
because they had gone dormant
because of a similar
resignation of a department
head.
>> okay.
So it's sort of a full circle.
>> 36 years later we're in the
same spot where people are
questioning and I've heard the
task force on pro-peace say
this is the reason why we don't
need these commissions.
The dysfunctional the directors
don't do their job.
>> it's just hurt my heart
because so many women not just
in this room in our community
spent hours providing the first
domestic violence policies
pretty much in california
in san francisco.
Most of you don't know we
didn't have a general order to
deal with domestic violence
until the 90s.
And because of the commission's
cooperation with the police
commission we have the first
general order developed.
>> and now we have a full on
sexual assault you know,
special victims unit which
expand it beyond domestic
violence.
The other thing that I feel
very proud that we did in the
nine years I served we set up
the guidelines for the sexual
harassment training the city
now is required to do wasn't
required in the 90s yet but
because of that the city
actually I don't think anybody
has recently quantified the
savings.
When I was appointed one of the
task we were asked to do was
try to divert some of the
complaints of sexual harassment
complaints within our city that
were going outside in private
lawsuits or the eeoc at the
time.
So what we tried to do is bring
it back inside and prevent it
from major litigation.
>> but I don't think anybody
really quantified what kind of
money were saved by the work of
our human resources department
every department has a human
resource department.
And I think, you know, you
might want to look into that.
But there were a lot of
concrete savings because of the
cooperation of the commission
says women city structure
and trying to improve the
condition of women's working
conditions here.
So thank you very much and have
a wonderful day
here.
>> thank you, carol ito.
Next up we will have our
district 11 supervisor chen.
>> thank you, PRESIDENT.
Has he fully in your hands?
I like a podium although I came
to the hospital.
>> good afternoon, colleagues.
Today I'm very thrilled to
honor myself how yang hung for
40 years of service masako has
been serving the community
through his work to uplift
guitar therapy and provide much
needed health care to our
residents in san francisco te
tai therapy it's a practice of
traditional chinese medicine
focused on treating injuries
that has been passed down for
thousands of years.
It combines bone setting soft
tissue manipulation and herbal
medicine techniques to address
pain in muscles, bones
and joints.
The history of chinese trauma
to comitology in the united
states dates back over 150
years to the chinese railroad
workers.
>> due to the limited access to
western health care at a time
to die, therapy became the
cultural practice and crucial
practice that hew and relieved
rear wheel workers injuries
from working in hazardous
conditions.
>> his father doc lam since
it's considered one of the top
ten foremost master of the
modern chinese orthopedics
and also and comitology master
has brought to carry his
father's legacy to bring the
long traditions of chinese to
talk therapy to our
communities.
>> in the 1980s marceau
immigrated to the united state
.
And in MAY 1999 he helped found
the american chinese medical
therapy association here in san
francisco, established it
exactly 20 years ago today the
american chinese medical
therapy association has fought
to continue the the tradition
of chinese mythology in san
francisco over the decades
and the association have
conducted training courses
and provided free treatments to
our community.
>> massaro has dedicated his
life to healing countless
patients and events in chinese
terminology making a lasting
impact on san francisco.
I'm very proud to honor him as
a whole and I also invite you
all to join me and to give him
a big round of applause
and possible and I'm going to
say a few words in chinese.
>> see, for these are things
I'm would like stricken
meursault whoi chan how seafood
you go hi treat those how we
have some but why you like you
though how seafood come get
whole see how how easy our laws
don't go for great hotel de san
francisco going into JUNE can
get caught why someone sees
these homes he
good afternoon my name's nancy
I'm a student of master hold
I'm going to do master home
have a really great statement
and I would like to translate
that in english so everybody
can share that.
>> okay, so here we go.
Dear honorable supervisors
and friends.
Good afternoon.
I am deeply honored to receive
this award during the
celebration of aapi heritage
month in this chamber on behalf
of the traditional chinese
medicine community tcm, I
extend my sincere gratitude to
all of you especially li two
supervisors shinya and chan's
supervisor connie chen for
their continued support of tcm
and talk therapy.
This award is a collective
honor for all of us in the
field.
I am grateful to be my beloved
father hojo lam one of china's
top ten orthopedic doctors of
modern time.
>> he passed on his exceptional
long arm to therapy techniques
to my five brothers and myself
and trinkle nicely outstanding
orthopedic specialists
in china.
>> I am incredibly grateful to
my wife to his wife juliana the
son stephen and to grant to
our grandchildren for their
and gravely encouragement
and support over the decades.
Tcm is profound enduring passed
down through generation as a
valuable cultural heritage of
chinese people.
>> more than 156 years ago
chinese railroad workers who
help build the transcontinental
railroad bought therapy with
them to treat injuries to
therapy has played a crucial
role in healing injuries caused
by work, sports and daily life
accidents.
The tmc community deeply
appreciates the proclamation of
MAY 28th as the title day in a
city and county of san
francisco.
I also sincerely appreciate the
tcm community in china for its
continuous support,
encouragement and dictated to
promote tcm rural by benefiting
people across the globe.
Finally the tcm community will
continue to collaborate with
all petitioners of chinese
medicine, acupuncture, herbal
medicine and talk therapy to
serve and heal more people
in the united states.
Wishing everyone happiness,
good health and prosperity.
>> thank you very much
.
>> district one supervisor chan
thank you PRESIDENT Mandarin
colleagues I have the honor
and privilege to recognize jia
li, director of the health care
system for after her two
decades of tenure at the san
francisco veterans affairs
health care system.
jess officially retired
and would love to have jia come
up to the podium directly is
the first aapi woman to lead
the san francisco va health
care system.
She is a distinguished health
care executive with over 25
years of leadership experience
in both the public and private
sectors.
Since her appointment as the
director for the va health care
system, she provided executive
oversight for $1 billion annual
operating budget the san
francisco va medical center,
nine va clinics and a community
living center and other
critical services that ensure
our veterans and patients
receive the care they need to
thrive.
From 2019 to 2020 to directly
serve as deputy director for
the san francisco va health
care system where she solidify
her reputation as a strategic
and forward thinking leader
committed to delivering
exceptional care to veterans
including expanding the
specialty care services
in northern california va
clinics all the way from santa
rosa to eureka.
>> launching of the memory care
unit a short term rehab unit
and a veteran's welcome center
spearheading the initiative to
improve referral coordination
and synchronization of
specialty care across a
veteran's integrated service
network.
Director lee holds a master of
business administration and a
bachelor of science
in psychology in physiology.
She is a certified fellow of
the american college of health
care executives and an active
member of the san francisco
marin seo section of the
hospital council of northern
and central california.
DR. Director lee is a visionary
leader with a deep commitment
to veterans health
and well-being.
We should all feel confident
that the foundation she has
laid out will continue to
uplift so many veterans in san
francisco and bay area for
years to come.
>> but colleagues, I wanted to
really share a personal story
about why DR. Lee is such a
treasure not just really to our
veterans community but I must
say who has been overseeing the
va hospital in the richmond.
There are veterans living
in san francisco throughout
in different neighborhoods
including the richmond
including one of the veterans
living in out of richmond who
really been there for a long
time.
But in last year really a
continuing increase of mental
health challenges.
It was very difficult for her
in the neighborhood and to
really figure out it is time
for her to have even more
intensive care.
And collectively with the
community we reach out to
director lee who has been so
amazing and responds live
and immediately with such a
compassion and care.
But most importantly just
amazing resources and still
strategic about it.
Within two weeks this veteran
was well care for finding a new
home with intensive care
and just being able to really
help the community and that
help all of us to be able to
remain compassion and to our
neighbor and really also care
for our veterans while being
I'm so sad to say that she is
officially retired.
>> I mean look at her.
She's too young.
I think in my humble opinion to
retire at this.
>> therefore I have great
vision for her.
I think that there's still much
more to come for her career.
I'm excited for her.
I think there is a lot to be
said about someone like her
and there's a great needs for
her talent in san francisco.
I look forward to seeing more
of you in different health care
system venues and perhaps
opportunity.
>> and thank you director lee.
We are just so grateful to you
and our veteran community is
very grateful to you and thank
you so much for your care.
And of course I think all your
va staff I have met them many
of them.
They also just really adore you
and thank you for your
leadership.
>> and the floor is yours for.
>> well good afternoon.
Respect to supervisors
and supervisor connie chen it
is a great honor to be here
today to receive this
accommodation.
>> didn't expect it.
I have served in san francisco
at the va for really over 2021
years and it is actually rare
to be in the same va for as
long as I have so I really grow
to love what we do.
>> our mission is very clear is
to take care of our veterans,
our nation's heroes who really
gave it all give their all to
serve our nation with great
honor.
So it is my honor to serve them
and give them and offer them
the best care possible.
At you shared a personal story
.
It is you know, veterans are
like our family.
We do take care of them.
I think that we it literature
has shown that the va health
care system really take care of
the veterans better than our
community resources.
>> so very, very proud of that.
But I remember when you came to
the hospital and visited
and you were really interested
as we were giving you the tour
of all of the type of services
that we offer our veterans
in the san francisco in the bay
area.
And actually we cover as you
mentioned all the way to the
oregon border in eureka clinic.
So so very, very honored
and happy to serve these san
francisco residents
and veterans as well.
So with that said, I yes, I
have energy.
I have a lot to give.
So if there's anything I can do
to contribute to this
community, I would love to do
so.
>> and I'll just say a few
things in mandarin for for our
guests.
>> well, she I immigrated here
back in 1980 so I consider
myself a san francisco
resident.
>> so
district nine supervisor
fielder thanks so much,
PRESIDENT.
>> first off, thank you so much
to supervisors chan and chan
for hosting aapi heritage lunch
at city hall today.
>> I would like to welcome
elaine yan and many lie to the
podium.
>> please give them a hand
today in honor of aapi heritage
month I am so proud to
officially commend elaine, jen
and many ly the owner
and manager of imperial garden
which has served thousands of
residents in the portola since
1995 open as a way to serve the
dining dreams of an ever
growing portola garden district
.
Elaine and many continue
elaine's family's legacy by
providing a cherished place
where families can connect
and enjoy traditional dimsum
and chinese cuisine.
Many and elaine grew up as best
friends and now form a dynamic
leadership team whose warmth
and dedication extends far
beyond the day to day.
Together they have created a
supportive, compassionate
community among staff customers
and the portland neighborhood
and imperial garden.
>> they have welcomed
generations of families
celebrating life's major
milestones building lasting
relationships through their
hospitality.
Elaine and many are both
incredibly committed to
bridging cultural
and generational divides
and connecting their team
members with organizations
and the broader community of
the portola.
>> elaine's family owned the
san bruno market just down the
street from where imperial
gardens stands where many would
visit her while she worked with
her parents to this day people
still recognize elaine and her
warm welcoming personality from
20 years ago with regulars
spanning decades.
Elaine and minnie's dedication
to their work does not go
unnoticed.
>> just as their customers are
so thankful to them for keeping
the restaurant running, both of
them feel it is important to
maintain a place for regulars
of all walks of life to call
home and a great example of
innovation found in many of our
immigrant communities many live
founded sassy foods within
imperial garden a vegan dim sum
menu that brings a unique
vision to the restaurant
reimagining traditional comfort
food that is accessible to all
.
>> inspired by her oakland
upbringing and chinese
vietnamese heritage, her plant
based dishes melds new
and traditional culinary
techniques evoking a sense of
nostalgia while offering
familiar flavors in a fresh,
thoughtful and inclusive way.
>> imperial garden elaine
and many not only are a source
of pride for the chinese
community in portola but also
bring in other communities
through the universal language
of food.
>> I am so proud to honor both
of them today.
they truly exemplify what makes
san francisco and specifically
district nine great.
And it is my privilege to honor
them for aapi heritage month.
>> thank you.
>> just for the record
committee and I have been best
friends since eighth grade.
>> you know as an adult as
parents this is a great honor
for us to be able to share this
moment together and we want to
thank everybody here.
Just a few weeks ago our
restaurant was able to have the
honor to host, you know, two
local nonprofit organizations
dear community and tag to
teachers association or chinese
teacher association.
And that's where we saw many of
the supervisors there to attend
which is our honor.
>> and you know, we're just
very grateful for this.
>> we're really looking forward
to working with supervisor
jackie and we do want to let
everybody know that this
recognition isn't for imperial
garden.
It's actually for our whole
district, for the whole
community.
We're just the representative
to come here and pick up
because most of us are small
business owners.
They can't leave their station
to come and get this so many
and I are going to be the
person to accept this award for
our community so will just be
posted at our restaurant
and that's it.
>> but we want to give a very
special shout out to the peony,
the portola neighborhood
association and they have their
represented here jen who is our
new corridor manager I have to
tell you it wasn't an easy
choice for us to come back
after covid.
We're still not there yet but
it was them that inspired me
because I grew up in the 90s
pretty much I was in that
neighborhood for over 30 plus
years and they've done a lot
for us and we know we're not
the only ones struggling in our
neighborhood.
We know the whole city is
and we really look forward to
working with everybody and we
want to recognize jen for being
here and being our photo person
as well.
>> so thank you very much for
this honor.
>> thank you.
Thank you to everyone for
giving us this award.
>> I do want to add on to what
supervisor said food is the
universal language and the
restaurant has been there for
three decades now we see
generations of family come
and go.
They celebrate, they cry.
So it's really special to us to
be able to be in the community
to offer this space for people
to have their memories because
food brings people together.
We remember the experiences of
the food not so much the food
and so that's why for us to be
recognized for having this
space as small business owners
as everyone MAY know, it's
really tough.
It's really tough for small
business owners and so we
really appreciate that and are
grateful.
>> hearts are full of love to
continue to give back to the
community in this way.
>> so thank you so much.
Thank you.
All right.
Thank.
>> all right.
A word on the next two
accommodations that will be
provided by supervisor dorsey.
It was a tradition of my
predecessor which I believe
in that each of us should only
be doing one commendation per
per 230 special order in very
rare circumstance is it is
possible that there MAY be
exceptions to this rule and the
confluence of national public
works week and the last week of
assistant chief lazar lazaro's
service to san francisco did
seem like a sufficient basis to
give supervisor dorsey the
dispensation to break our
rules.
>> this one time supervisor
dorsey thank you.
>> thank you so much PRESIDENT
Randleman colleagues it is my
great honor to recognize
someone I've had the privilege
of working with and learning
from during my own time in city
service one of san francisco's
most dedicated, most well
respected and accomplished
public safety and civic leaders
is assistant chief of police
david lazaar.
>> now as the current assistant
chief and chief of operations
for san francisco's police
department, david lazaar holds
one of the highest ranking
and most prestigious posts
in the department overseeing
field operations.
Special operations
investigations, the airport
bureau and the community
engagement division.
It's a role that reflects not
only the trust he has earned
but the depth of experience
and leadership he brings to his
job.
That leadership journey started
right here in san francisco.
David is a fourth generation
san franciscans who grew up
in the sunset and richmond
districts graduated from
downtown high school in the
mission and began his service
as a teenager first as a police
activities league cadet
and then as a police dispatcher
.
Inspired by his mother, also a
dispatcher, he was called to a
life of public safety early on
.
He joined S.F. P.D. In 1991
and steadily worked his way up
the ranks from patrol officer
to sergeant from sergeant to
inspector, from inspector to
tenant and eventually to
captain to commander to deputy
chief and now assistant chief.
He has personally served
in eight of our city's ten
district stations and commanded
ten different assignments
across nearly every one of S.F.
Pd's bureaus.
Assistant chief eleazar has led
S.F. Pd's preparations for some
of our city's largest and best
known events from super bowl 50
to apec.
>> and he has played key roles
in devising, launching
and leading transformative
public safety initiatives.
He created operation outreach
to coordinate the department's
response to homelessness and in
2018 helped to open the city's
healthy streets operation
center or h soc a model of
cross-agency collaboration that
endures today to more
effectively ameliorate street
conditions in real time.
In 2017 as a commander he
established the department's
first ever community engagement
division.
He personally oversaw 60 of the
272 U.S. Department of justice
recommendations for 21st
century police reform.
Helping to shape a long term
strategy for community policing
and accountability that
continues to guide the
department today and that
serves as an inspiration to
18,000 police departments
in this country.
On a personal note, I had the
privilege of working alongside
assistant chief eleazar when I
served as chief of police
communications director for two
years.
I watched him lead with
integrity, empathy
and professionalism at a very
difficult time for law
enforcement in this country.
Never losing sight of why we do
this work to serve the people
of san francisco and to provide
safety with respect.
>> he's also a lifetime learner
and teacher, a police academy
instructor since 1998 and a
graduate of harvard's kennedy
school of government, the
senior management institute for
police and other top tier
leadership programs.
He holds a degree in project
management from st mary's
college and continues to mentor
the next generation of public
safety leaders.
today we recognize not just an
assistant chief but someone who
has spent his entire life
in service to the city he loves
and who continues to serve it
with distinction and heart.
On behalf of a grateful city,
we congratulate you on your
retirement and we thank you,
chief eleazar, for your
leadership, for your example
and for your unwavering
commitment to san francisco.
Now I know I have colleagues on
the roster who want to add
their own expressions of
gratitude but then by a
tradition we are now well
establishing here at the board
of supervisors we will present
you with that universally
acknowledged recognition of
excellence in policing.
>> donuts congrats to you.
It was our no I think super app
before you get started.
>> supervisor walton, thank you
so much.
>> first of all, assistant
chief lazo, I know that we have
not always seen eye to eye but
I just want to say to you that
I know that your work and your
entire career was dedicated to
making sure that all san
francisco residents were safe.
And so I want you to know that
I appreciate that and thank you
for your service for all of
these years and wish you the
best and your future endeavors
in your retirement.
Thank you so much for your
service.
Thank you.
>> supervisor melgar thank you
so much.
>> supervisor dorsey for doing
this for assistant chief as our
and I wanted to just take the
opportunity to tell you how
much I appreciate you.
You are a resident of district
seven and I also appreciate
your amazing wife who has also
provided powerful and support.
>> I don't know how I'm going
to do this job without you
frankly.
You have besides all the kudos
that supervisor dorsey just
outlined.
You are one of the most
emotionally intelligent people
I've ever met.
You have this personality that
can see what people are feeling
and then just connect the dots
which is pretty rare.
And I don't know how we're
going to get through, you know,
the safety issues that we form,
things that we still have to
do.
You know, without you there,
you know, to council or cajole,
guide, provide thoughtful
commentary and guidance to all
of us in what we're doing.
So I know you're still going to
be around and I appreciate you
and couch you as a friend.
So I am so glad that you're
still going to, you know, be
with us in the city.
I'm going to sorely MISS You
in this position.
You have always been so
responsive, so available.
Your heart is always in it
and I have never for a moment
doubted your motivations
and your deep commitment to
what we're doing.
So from the bottom of my heart
thank you so much for what
you've done and continue to do.
And I also want to thank your
outstanding family for having
provided the support because
it's not easy for the family to
do what they do in the jobs
that we have.
>> so thank you all.
Thanks, julie.
Thank you.
Soup for viser mahmood really
bummed that I'm losing all the
people I used to talk to in my
district from east lazard to
two captains but it's been
really exciting to continue to
see your engagement and to see
that we have two amazing new
captains as well as captain
nobles in the back.
I see.
I wanted to knowledge you
and you are on on two things
one is just how much we hear
about you regularly in the
community.
I know there are members here
from the tenderloin.
You want to raise your hand?
Who came out just to support
you?
And I think that this speaks to
how much they see the work
you've championed
and prioritize.
Know the camera network was a
brainchild and a baby of your
of your leadership and that's
something I hear about on a
regular basis from people
in the tenderloin who
appreciate the impact it's had
on keeping our community safe.
>> you're your impact on these
communities is so strong that I
walk through chinatown one day
and there is a man playing a
violin who has your photo from
I don't know of 10 or 15 years
ago attached to his violin
and I was like wait the guy his
hair is a little different but
I think it's the same guy
and it just shows at every
level across the city.
>> you've had a personal impact
on so many people in keeping us
safe, keeping us feel connected
and I think that just speaks to
how responsive you are and how
you prioritize the needs of the
community.
Really bummed to see you leave
but really appreciate the
service that you've provided
for decades to these respective
neighborhoods.
So thank you.
Thank you.
Super visor solder boy seals
are I'm so glad to see you get
this much deserved recognition.
I want to let it be known
before you were here we had you
first in district three and I
know many years later almost
some ten years on your your
name and your model in central
station is still followed.
It's still recalled and I think
captains after you even all
these years later look to to
lead and look to learn from
your um from your model that
you set in central station.
You know I was starting in my
neighborhood association as you
were our captain in central
and I can't tell you how many
times we had conversations
about a concern in the
community and very quickly you
know, someone said call the
captain and very quickly things
were taken care of and we felt
secure.
We felt confident and it felt
like a relationship.
It felt like a partnership
and I think that is what your
department aims for is that
community policing models those
relationships.
So thank you for always leading
and we're very proud of you.
>> thank you.
Thank you.
Supervisor chan thank you.
>> PRESIDENT Randleman
assistant chief officer I think
we go like way back, you know.
In fact I want to say that many
have known assistant chief
eleazar in a very friendly
and like great community
setting.
I think one of the things that
I learned from assistant chief
eleazar at the time was really
in fact the passing of rose
pack in chinatown was a very
serious and somber time but he
remained calm and making sure
that community was informed
and very transparent with the
investigation and the results
and everything that to make
sure that he understood the the
really what it meant for the
community.
And I think the key to that was
something that I think what I
took away from about you as a
person not just about our
assistant chief or captain at
that time is the fact that you
fundamentally care for the
community.
And I think the the fact that
you also care about at least
from me chinatown where I grew
up and it's like it's tough
and yet me and over the years
you spoke the best chinese
and the great chinese greeting
during the lunar new year just
amazed everybody everybody so
floor but it's not because just
because you know with a great
sense of humor but really I
think it's great level of care
it's a great level of care for
for someone like you to to care
for the community even long
after you're no longer the
captain for central station.
And I agree I couldn't concur
with supervisor malcolm more
what it means like your you
have amazing family your
daughter your wife just seeing
them in the community
in chinatown with you and how
loving and kind they always
been that speaks in volume that
is not just about who you are
but you're just your entire
family and know that your
family it's also truly is also
in public service and serving
the city and I think that we're
just really grateful for a
great family of public servant.
You will be MISS But then at
the same time you should be so
proud of the career that you
have left behind.
We're also just grateful.
>> thank you.
Thank you supervisor chen thank
you, chief.
>> plus assistant chief lazor
as another daughter of
chinatown I said before I I'm
in this role you know we
already have something already
have engagement and I know
about the community loves you
and we appreciate you the
community engagement, the
community building the
community trust that you that
you are trying to make sure
that that community feels safe
.
I don't think that's words that
we can express to the world
and the services and the
leadership that you have
demonstrated in the last
decades.
>> and I also want to say
personally that I really,
really appreciate that you make
yourself available.
>> you're very responsive.
>> you are sharing ideas
and how to help someone like me
who's new to to continue to
hone in to community safety
and community engagement.
Thank you for those advice
and thank you for your
leadership again and and thank
you for your family in many,
many locations.
They were out there and I know
family's always the backbone
and always the biggest
supporter to someone who is
able to dedicate years of
service and serving the public.
>> thank you.
Thank you.
Super visor and engardio.
>> I know you raised through
the ranks and hold a lot of
high positions in the police
department but I think what's
most important is how well you
model what it means to be a
police officer in an honorable
serving officer in san
francisco.
And I hope the young people
that we're trying to recruit to
be officers will look at your
example and want to follow
in your footsteps because
you've been responsive, you
care, you show up and you
connect with people and that's
the most important part of
police work.
So thank you for your service
to the city.
>> thank you supervisors cheryl
you deserve an enormous amount
of enjoyment but I just want to
ask you not to be a stranger
because your service in this
city means so much and I know
you've got a lot of chapters
left in you and I'm really
excited to see what's next from
you.
>> so thank you very much.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.
My colleagues have said almost
everything that I would say but
it has occurred to me in my
seven years on this board of
supervisors that if there is a
public safety challenge facing
the san francisco police
department, david lazer will be
thrown at it and will be asked
to solve it.
>> you are you have been the
swiss army knife of sfpd and we
are all grateful for the work
that you've done.
I've you know, mentioned here
on numerous occasions that I
think this is the last ten
years have been a time of
unprecedented challenges for
policing not just in san
francisco but nationally that
our S.F. Pd has made remarkable
strides and in many ways become
a model and had to deal with
challenges that not all police
departments have to and your
skill and your bosses skill
in addressing that has been
remarkable and something I have
very much appreciated and I
would echo supervisor melgar
his comments about julie who is
a gift to san francisco and I
am a big fan of hers as well.
Before we let you speak we
probably should let chief scott
say a few words if you would
like to.
>> chief scott.
>> thank you.
Thank you, PRESIDENT.
Gentlemen, what do I say that
hasn't been said except for I
love this guy.
He is one of the hardest
working people that I've ever
been around.
His dedication to this city is
unmatched.
He loves this department, loves
this city and will do anything
to make it work.
So you know, when I first met
david a new knew right away
that he was a special person
and I told him that as well.
But I want to thank you all for
recognizing his work because
it's as my mom used to say,
give people flowers when they
hear to smell them and you gave
him flowers today so we're free
and honest.
And to to his family to julie
is are adriana grace your son
today?
>> yeah.
So I did see they are talk
about support.
I first met grace seems the
last order but she's at all the
community events all the at all
the department events and I've
got to know and love them as
well because I know how hard it
is on families to do to allow
us to do what we do.
So I just want to say thank you
and you got a lot of support
here from people in blue
uniform and a lot of support
here from people in the
community and you deserve every
single phrase that you've
gotten.
>> so thank you, david.
Thank you very much.
>> and now assistant chief
lazaro.
>> all right.
I was going to hold it together
within when chief scott came
up.
That's that's where I'm
breaking down for a moment.
>> this is really just a very
surreal moment for me 33.5
years and I just I want to make
it about all of you just for
just a moment.
Thank you.
Supervisor dorsey, it was a
pleasure to work with you.
I thank you for all your
support.
I will put the donuts on form
700 after I eat all of them
today so thank you very much
for your kindness.
Supervisor souder thank you so
much for your kind words.
It was a pleasure working with
you in district three you
outpace me on cantonese 10 to 1
so I look forward to seeing
your great work supervisor shen
thank you.
Thank you for what you do
in district 11.
>> we've been on the phone.
You're all about public safety
and I'm grateful for you and so
thank you very much for your
kind words.
>> supervisor fielder we didn't
get to know each other but if
we did we would have been best
of friends working together
and I'm sorry we didn't have a
chance to work longer together.
But congratulations on all your
success.
>> supervisor melgar thank you
for holding down district seven
on the west side.
Thank you for being our great
supervisor and doing so much
for our families and all of us
that are out there on that side
and it's been a pleasure to
work with you and I'm grateful
for your your public safety
and really getting things done
out there.
I'm so thankful.
president mendelsohn we've been
together from the beginning
and I thank you as well
and really the support of the
S.F. Pd that you give every day
means a lot to our officers
just like all your colleagues.
It means a lot to our
department and the amount of
care that you give and date
we're right there with you.
I know we got a lot more work
to do and you're in good hands.
I can see in the back.
>> so thank you, supervisor
walton.
We have a lot in common.
>> don't don't don't believe
the disagreements.
You know we have in common is
public safety.
We both care so much about
making our city safe and that's
why you and I always feel
aligned.
So I'm so thankful to know you
and have worked with you
and and got to meet you so many
years ago.
Thank you supervisor chen you
know I she just walk down
and pull those retirement
papers until I give you a
couple of beat cops on clement
street but I think you're
in good hands with captain
canning and it's going to
happen and I'm grateful for all
your kind words and everything
you said to me and so thank you
so very much and I definitely
will see you in chinatown.
Hopefully you recognize me
there but I'll be there
supervising guardian.
Thank you from day one the only
supervisor that went to a
police station and interviewed
every single police officer
and said who what is it to be a
police officer and what do you
need from the board of
supervisors that went a long
way with with all of us and I
thank you for promoting public
safety supervisor mahmud you
hit the ground running in the
tenderloin.
You're everywhere you do so
much for the community.
It was a pleasure to know you
before you were a supervisor
and district five is very very
very lucky to have you and we
in the department are grateful
that you're in that seat
and then supervisor cheryl I
don't know what the future
holds but I do know that having
spent my entire life in the san
francisco police department,
it's time for the next chapter
time to take a break.
Time to to take care of the
honey do list, another reason
to pull papers and then come
back to work.
But I'm going to get it done
and I will see you around to my
lovely wife of 31 years who had
a incredible 25 year career
in the san francisco police
department breaking glass
ceilings as a woman that did
such a tremendous job.
I always say that she's the
modern day dirty harry but she
did it and she's been my boss
right by my side and without my
wife julie there would be no
david lazaar in san francisco
without her without her raising
our kids I mean if I switch
places with her she would be
standing here as the assistant
chief much smarter than me.
So I thank you for all your
support and love julie.
>> I thank you very much.
I want to thank we have three
children two of which are here.
>> nicholas is the only work
guy working today.
Obviously but for adriana
and grace so thankful for our
two daughters it's hard to be
the kids of cop parents very
challenging especially when we
give so much to the city.
There's such a trade off and I
want to thank you for your
sacrifice and you two are the
best children a dad and a mom
could ever have and we love you
so much and the fact you're
here today means so much to me.
>> so thank you.
And grace's grace's boyfriend
zo is here as well.
Sacred heart cathedral.
Thank you so very much.
>> I want to thank my mom,
donna, who's sitting here
in the front row, a single mom
in san francisco raising an
only child.
That's me going to public
school barely making ends meet.
But she worked hard to raise me
in 1982 she stepped up to the
call to be a911 dispatcher for
31 years.
She did that role when there
was 1 or 1 california active
shooter.
She was on that radio channel
for eight hours and managed
that entire incident and we are
a family called to serve this
public serve the public.
We're a family called to give
something greater than
ourselves and it's been such an
honor and I'm really thankful,
mom, that you're here and I
love you very much and thank
you.
>> I don't want I don't want to
be long winded but you have
great people in the san
francisco police department
and I just want to give a shout
out to DR. Roach who's here.
>> yes.
>> rene rene coppola, thank you
for being here.
Steven lopez I want doreen to
raise her hand.
>> doreen doreen is my
assistant who pulls it all
together for me.
Thank you, doreen.
>> officer loretta jimenez is
here.
Thank you, captain noble in the
back.
Let's keep that tenderloin
going.
>> keep it safe.
We got work to do.
>> I want to thank the quiet
leadership in the back that is
basically running operations
between commander of integral
from the golden gate division,
commander jackson from the
metro division and your newly
promoted right a hot off the
press.
>> derek lieu, deputy chief of
field operations thank you very
much.
>> the department is in great
hands and I'll make sure that
all of you have his telephone
number so you can call him day
and night.
>> he is ready.
I thank all the community
that's here is john and kate
from the tenderloin.
Julie, I see you sally leon who
was mayor lee's confidential
secretary that made her way to
the police department has been
such a great supportive and a
great supportive role.
>> thank you sally.
>> I hope I'm not missing
anybody but I want to save the
last for the chief hero.
Oh, nathan bernard for my team.
Nathan thank you for being my
right hand guy.
Lieutenant kenya league thank
you can and the last thing I
want to say is I want to thank
our chief of police bill scott
who was not only the longest
serving chief in the last 55
years but did so much for this
department that he brought us
to the modern era.
He brought from another
jurisdiction and came here with
the idea of making the san
francisco police department the
best in the world.
And there's no chief that I can
think about that on a volunteer
basis took 272 recommendations
and implemented them.
He's the chief that had enough
trust and confidence in me to
put me on his command staff for
the last eight years.
I want to thank you chief, for
all your support for your
mentorship, for your guidance,
for being gracious, teaching me
how to be gracious, teaching me
how to be patient, teaching me
humility.
I learned more from you than
anyone else that I can think
of.
I'm super grateful that you're
my boss.
I'm super thankful that you
have led a department that has
brought crime down, that has
brought technology to the
forefront and it has been an
honor of a lifetime to work for
you, chief.
And I'm so very thankful and I
wish the very best for you on
your next assignment and your
next endeavor.
>> and I thank you, chief scott
and I love you as well.
Thank you.
>> and with that thank you very
much.
It's been an honor of a
lifetime.
Thank you.
Leave that mike.
Hold on.
Supervisor dorsey, I think my
colleagues are going to insist
that we bring and we bring
assistant chief lazaro into the
well and maybe the chief can
join as well.
>> okay.
Thank you.
My family all the S.F. Pd
people, all my family
down here with the same idea.
All right.
One, two, three.
Just sorry.
Apologies my phone.
One, two, three.
One, one one, two, three.
All right, I got it.
I got I got I'll stick around
if I can make a public comment.
I let that just go after that
you got some nice very nice.
Thank you.
And just waiting here for I
don't even feel like you know,
everyone is gonna know.
Thank you so much for being
here.
Thank you mary thank you know
okay yeah yeah so dorsey so
he's got public works best just
come on you.
>> and then there are three
more supervised the dorsey
round to thank you colleagues
because of a confluence of
worthy endeavors to celebrate
and recognize this week as
PRESIDENT Randleman mentioned I
proudly double dip today for
public works week to commend
six outstanding public servants
whose daily work typically done
with little fanfare makes a
profound difference in the
lives of san franciscans as
well as the experience of those
who visit our city for their
unwavering commitment to our
city and its guests
and especially to the
communities and visitors to the
district I represent district
six please join me
in recognizing corey jackson.
Dominique charles michael
lerner deli, jackie wilson,
henry ramirez and milton
navarrette.
These these six individuals
represent the very best of what
public service should look like
their work through san
francisco public works touches
every corner of our city but
their dedication to some of the
most complex, challenging
and high impact areas
in district six is what truly
stands out from south of market
and east.
Cut to mission bay and the
embarcadero these neighborhoods
depend on the quiet excellence
of people like corey,
dominique, michael, jackie,
henry and milton individuals
who show up day in and day out
to clean our streets report
and respond to emergencies,
support residents and restore
order and dignity to our public
spaces.
District six faces many
challenges.
Public safety issues.
Behavioral health challenges.
Overburdened infrastructure.
And I can tell you firsthand
our ability to respond as a
city is only as strong as the
front line workers doing that
work.
Each of these public servants
has not only shown consummate
professional wisdom but also a
genuine concern and care for
the people who live in our
neighborhoods whether it's
removing hazards from our
sidewalks, coordinating
cleanups in partnership with
the community or responding to
residents with empathy
and urgency their service goes
far beyond a job description.
It's personal, it's principled
and it is deeply appreciated.
Too often in this building we
focus on the high level
decisions and the policy
debates and those are important
but it's equally important that
we recognize those who make the
city work.
Corey dominick, michael jackie
henry and milton are not just
workers.
They are trusted partners
in our city's recovery.
They're the ones restoring
faith in public systems through
their action.
They're often the first city
employees our residents
interact with and in many cases
they are the reason those
residents continue to believe
in the potential of san
francisco.
So today I want to say thank
you.
Thank you, corey.
Thank you, dominic.
Thank you, michael.
Thank you, jackie.
Thank you, henry.
And thank you, milton.
Your exemplary service is what
it means to be a public
servant.
you do it with humility,
consistency and heart.
The neighborhoods of district
six are better and our city is
stronger because of you.
And although it's an honor we
normally reserved for sworn
police officers, my office
decided as an offering that
might be better appreciated
than flowers and because we
were at the donut shop anyway
to present you with donuts also
as well as the certificates of
appreciation and gratitude for
all of you.
And I have some colleagues who
want to say some kind words to
you as well.
>> thanks so much and well
first I suggested early I
recognize that those are bob's
donuts on poster two district
three business so I like this
trend of donuts instead of
flowers.
Let's keep doing that.
But I know just quickly I want
to echo that sentiment
and thank public works your
employees, all of you here
and one of the the highlights
of the last few months
in office has been getting to
go out with some of your
colleagues and do the clean
corridors mornings and we were
just on hyde street this week
in stockton before that.
So seeing firsthand the hard
work you do, I appreciate it.
Please know that the residents
of san francisco appreciate it.
You are out there on the front
lines doing really, really
important and hard work
and thank you for all your
service and your supervisor
there.
>> mahmood al-zahar has
acknowledged everyone in public
works for this of this
commendation.
You guys keep our streets paved
clean but also safe.
I know corey your you operate
indymac uh, a couple of times
and that's something a lot of
people don't recognize the
streets of the tenderloin are
safer because of the work that
you are doing with public works
out in the streets.
And I also wanted to
acknowledge that I know your
father, reverend arnold
townsend would be very proud of
the work you continue to do
in the district and in the
city.
You have very big shoes to fill
but you're leading a really
strong, strong leadership
in public works.
I'm excited to see and partner
with you in the years ahead.
>> so thank you for everything
personally the floor is yours.
Thank you.
Our teams at public works are
magnanimous and it's such a
reward and privilege to work
alongside them too.
And for the three 6524 seven
operational laborers who do not
so glamorous work.
Wow.
Thank you two hours zombie crew
and additional nbc s crews we
thank you for your tireless
work day in and day out to our
matriarchs for watering our
successes, honoring and lifting
up our public works leadership
director carla short deputy
director of operations to jada
durden our policy
and communications manager
rachel rachel gorton government
affairs manager I and schneider
all of our superintendents, all
zone supervisors special
acknowledgment to our
tenderloins selma union square
supervisor previously nicole de
la garza and currently the
colleague alongside of me MR.
Corey jackson to my immediate
manager ramsay's for believing
that I could do this work.
I after being a native and a
part to the city and county for
23 years post a career at five
keys and having a master's
degree reminded me to never
give up and hold my head high
while doing it.
Our program analysts ines
harris and tracy lawrence, my
fellow outreach coordinators at
public works, my gladiators
shannon sweeney and rayne wong,
michelle and annie
and community engagement team
all of our family and friends
who support us in this life's
work and transparency.
See I tend to work on
coordinating and liaising while
these amazing humans beside me
do the dirty work.
I also support support our
community by enforcement.
However I get to take photos of
them doing their magical fairy
duties by cleaning up things
the average person would scoff
at which feels odd but this is
a reminder that every once in a
while your work is seen.
It is valued and it is
appreciated.
I would like to highlight
highlights are ap I colleagues
and on memorial day weekend
military personnel who died
in service to our country to
the various community benefits
districts in sydney city
and county partnering agencies
specifically S.F. Pd and S.F.
Mta who worked on this specific
illegal dumping that was done
twice on minna if the highest
human act is to inspire and be
inspired this stands out.
San francisco has always
prioritized addressing the root
cause to fix the entire tree.
San francisco like the phenix
she is will rise through the
ashes as we have always done
in public works.
Our workplace core values are
our daily guiding principles
respect, integrity
and responsiveness we hold
in the highest regard excuse me
that acknowledgment and that we
continue to do our utmost best
day in and day out.
Many thanks to PRESIDENT
Mendelsohn and the members of
the board and supervisors
supervisor mahmud and our
district six supervisor dorsey
for the commendation in the
recognition this will never be
forgotten in the office we go
by one team and one dream
always in community.
Thank you very very much.
Thank you so so all right.
D-10 supervisor caesar walton
thank you so much.
>> PRESIDENT, MADAM
And colleagues it is my honor
to celebrate asian-american
and pacific islander heritage
month a time to uplift the
leaders and cultures that
continue to shape our
community.
Today I have the privilege of
recognizing someone whose
leadership embodies the very
spirit of this celebration.
Christine maui maria of all my
users christine, would you
please come up?
christine is a powerful example
of what resilience service
and a love for community look
like in action as the executive
director of all my usos she has
turned personal tragedy into a
lasting legacy of healing
and hope.
After losing her husband jt
maguire to stomach cancer
in 2018 christine made the
courageous decision to carry
forward his mission not just
in his memory but as a lifeline
to so many in need.
Christine your work through all
my usos has been
transformational.
You have expanded access to
vital health screenings,
created pathways to mental
health support and fought for
the resources that pacific
islander families need
and deserve.
You built a space where culture
healing and justice come
together and you've done it all
while navigating your own
journey of grief and strength
and a world that often
overlooks pacific islander
voices you have made sure they
are heard.
You have stood up for the
overlooked, advocated for the
underserved and continue to
show up for your community even
when it was not easy.
That kind of leadership is not
taught in books.
It comes from lived experience
.
It's from a deep sense of
responsibility and from the
kind of love that does not
quit.
I hope you know your impact
reaches far beyond your
organization.
you've helped shift the
narrative.
You've helped build a more
compassionate city and you've
reminded all of us that when we
center the most vulnerable
among us, we build a future
where everyone can thrive as we
honor asian-american
and pacific islander heritage
month we celebrate you not just
for what you've endured but for
what you've created.
On behalf of myself and the
entire district ten community
thank you.
We are better because of you.
>> seven years ago my husband
took his last breath and it
sent me into a dark place.
I've been doing work in the
community behind the scenes for
over 30 years now but it wasn't
until that moment that I was
thrown to the front to be to
lead.
>> I'm honored and I'm humbled
to be standing here today.
It takes a village to support
an entire family and to meet
the needs of the community.
And in this case my village is
our board, our community
members, our staff are among
staff.
>> DR. Patsy tito with the
someone community development
center.
Sylvia selinger with lattanzi
and a host of other cbos
and community members that came
out to support myself while I
was in that storm.
And to help us put together all
my uso's and help us grow
and just do the work that we
can do in the community to
support families that were
going through similar trauma
that like I was and others.
i like to thank the city of san
francisco and all of the
supervisors here today for
trusting all my uso's
in partnering partnering with
us and investing into our
pacific islander community.
Last but not least I like to
thank sherman walton and your
entire team for not overlooking
the pacific islanders and or
the the p-I and aapi month
and including a widow like me
who just wanted to serve the
community.
>> so thank you so much pie
and aapi right next district
for supervisor and engardio.
Thank you.
Colleagues today I'm honoring
the dance groups from the
sunset district.
I want to invite the dance
groups to come.
Everyone to come up so they can
see your beautiful costumes.
Come stand up.
There's the front.
Come on up.
To see all your beautiful
costumes just come down.
>> him in granddaddy of hong
kong MAY lead a full so earlier
today these remarkable senior
women performed at civic center
plaza.
They are all proudly in their
60s, 70s and even 80s and they
are ambassadors of chinese
culture in our city they dance
at nearly every major cultural
community event in the sunset
the autumn moon festival, the
chinese new year celebrations
at the sunset night market
and the opening of sunset dunes
.
Their presence has become so
central to the sunset
neighborhoods that they're now
featured in a mural at
terryville street and 22nd
avenue.
I'm also recognizing these
women for promoting senior
health and creating community.
Many had never danced before
joining a group they learned
together by teaching one
another and studying videos at
home and they practiced
multiple times a week.
The san francisco dance group
led by amy sy has been
practicing outside the ortega
public library for 16 years.
When I visited a rehearsal of
one of the dance groups it felt
less like a practice and more
like a family.
Many women formed new
friendships and cared for one
another maintaining a healthy
emotional and social life.
Equally important, I'm honoring
these women for their
remarkable resilience
and adaptation.
I want to share the story of
lisa su, leader of the san
francisco happy dancing team.
As an example, lisa came to the
united states at age 50,
leaving behind a career as a gm
appraiser in china.
To support her daughter she
took a job cleaning at the
airport years of physical
labor.
On top of bending her neck over
to appraise the gems led to
spinal issues that required
surgery.
When physical therapy did not
help lisa turned to dance
and what started as recovery
became a passion and a way to
lead and connect with others.
Today she still cares for her
husband and grandson yet
continues to dance with joy
and serve her community despite
being seniors themselves.
These women frequently perform
for free at senior centers
across san francisco.
They remind us that wellness is
more than just physical health
it's cultural pride connection
and joy and purpose at every
stage of life.
In honor of aapi heritage month
please join me in celebrating
these dance groups.
They prove that vitality
and service to the community
really have no age limit.
So sophie from my staff will do
a translation for everyone.
So if you could quick
translation.
>> yes.
Well, we should ensure that
jen's younger days aphasia
cindy
joe go recently
supervisors and guest.
>> I'm the leader of san
francisco happy dancing team.
My name is alisa shu.
Today we're honored to be
invited to perform at city hall
civic center plaza to celebrate
aapi heritage month.
>> we're very delighted
and proud to
please accept our genuine
gratitude to the city
government supervisors
and especially your supervisor
joe and guardian of the sunset
district for creating this
platform for us to perform
chinese dances and promote the
chinese cultural legacy making
it part of the american culture
.
>> should use a special member
amy tai who was my most
respected dance teacher.
She's also the leader
and teacher of san francisco
dancing team three
.
>> her dance team was founded
in 2009 16 years ago.
It has expanded from four
people at the beginning to more
than 80 members now.
>> she was the first to
introduce square dance into san
francisco.
The girls of her team shows how
square dancing is very popular
and they perform at various
locations just as joel said.
And their performances are
well-liked by neighbors
and highly regarded people who
want
.
>> we have performed multiple
times at chinese new year
celebrations, ottoman
festivals, night market elderly
homes and recently will perform
at the opening of the great
highway's new park sunset dunes
and we're well-liked
and therefore will welcome the
supervisors and officials to
connect with us more, create
more opportunities for us to
perform and possibly find
financial support for us which
will enable us to dance more
and better to preserve chinese
cultural legacy and pay back to
the society.
>> thank you again.
>> so one thing that
my name is amy is horn.
I'm the dance teacher of san
francisco community dance
group.
We're honored to be invited by
surprising garcia's office to
perform for aapi heritage
month.
our dance group was founded
eight years ago and our mission
is to serve the community
bringing health and joy to
those who watch our
performances.
We just like to express our
gratitude to those who
organized today's performance
and work hard to make it
happen.
Thank you, stacy.
Stacy, can we invite you to
speak briefly
?
>> hello everyone.
My name is stacy wong.
We are the sunset district
dance troupe.
We are very happy that we got
to participate in the mae api
celebration.
Our dance team has been
established in the community
for 25 years and we exercise at
the sunset rec center with new
members joining us every year.
We've learned many different
types of dances and have
participated in various
community service events.
We're grateful for the
opportunity today and thank you
to the supervisors and audience
for your enthusiastic support.
>> we hope to see you again
next year.
Thank you.
>> so let me and suprising
engardio is taking his honorees
out.
>> thank you for moving us
along and I would like to give
a special shout out to the
students from daniel webster
school and supervisor walton's
district.
>> make some noise for the
daniel webster students
and thank you natalie g for
letting us know.
All right.
And now with apologies to sin
huang and her family who have
been waiting for a very long
time sin can you come forward?
It's a special commendation for
patients colleagues in honor of
asian-american pacific islander
heritage month and cutup b
week.
It is my great honor to present
a special commendation to
cynthia or sin wang although
she wears many hats and does
many things in san francisco,
she currently serves among
them.
She currently serves as the
urban planning representative
on the san francisco
entertainment commission.
Sin was appointed to the
commission by maryland
and breed in MAY 2020 and has
sir has served as vice
PRESIDENT Of the commission
since late last last year.
>> in her day job she leads
business development at whang
insurance, a business founded
by her immigrant parents in the
outer sunset in 1979.
>> today she works there with
her parents, two sisters
and their 20 staff serving the
insurance needs of families
and small businesses including
over 1000 restaurants and bars
including manny's andy town,
coffee pacific cocktail haven,
horse feather and many more
across san francisco
and california.
But she does more than
insurance.
She's also helped hundreds of
business owners navigate
various aspects of our city's
bureaucracy, including those
struggling to comply with what
was until this this spring the
successful business entrance
program which thanks colleagues
to your support earlier this
year we have reform due to be
far less onerous beyond the
front door program and thank
you sin for your help
and thinking that through
previously sin managed global
public policy at airbnb
and before that served as a
foreign service officer at the
state department during the
obama administration with tours
abroad at the U.S. Embassies
in san jose, costa rica and the
us consulate in toronto,
canada.
She's also served as deputy
city attorney for the city of
hayward and provided legal
counsel to south san francisco
and los altos hills.
She's a graduate of smith
college and uc davis school of
law began her career at a firm
where I spent some time maya's
navy where but she unlike me,
coauthored several chapters of
the 2009 california land use
practice guide.
She's a recipient of the
planned parenthood golden gate
key of choice award for her
reproductive rights activism
and multiple meritorious honor
awards from the U.S. Department
of state.
And she was called a voice of
young feminism by the national
organization for women.
Sin was born in san francisco
and resides in the sunset
district with her wife tessa
and daughter sloane, who's
currently student council
PRESIDENT At jefferson
elementary school.
>> thank you.
Send for your service to san
francisco on the entertainment
commission and off and now the
floor is yours.
>> thank you.
>> oh, but before that
supervisor mahmud would like to
say I would like to also say
some things about you.
>> hasan hi.
>> it's was a very delightful
surprise to see you come
in today.
>> you've been an amazing
friend but also a leader in san
francisco.
We started our friendship by
you giving me dating advice
and then now that I was engaged
I thought that would stop
and now it's just relationship
advice.
But we're really grateful for
your friendship and support.
But I wanted to also just
acknowledge two things that I
really love about you are your
moral clarity and your
perseverance on behalf of the
city.
I know you've been a fierce
advocate for housing but also a
palestinian rights and I think
those two things came to a head
in some context where we heard
earlier today from carol how
she saw the children of the
tenderloin experiencing the
youth festival and the joy it
brought them and some people
think insurance is a boring
thing but I didn't know this
until this fair was over which
was that no insurance company
wanted to provide the insurance
for the event because we had a
deejay.
Something else to look into
apparently automatically gets
flagged.
>> but your firm came in at the
end to save the fair to ensure
that it was actually had
insurance that the show could
go on and the children could
have joy for an afternoon
and so I think that just spoke
to again a confluence of your
moral principles, your advocacy
and the way that your work is
behind so much of what makes
san francisco an amazing place
and the commitment you've done
without even asking for an
accolade on that I was really
delighted to see learn about
that after the fear was over.
So thank you again for all you
do for san francisco and for
helping me get married to so
thank you.
>> thank you.
Thank you supervisors.
It is an incredible honor to be
here today receiving this
commendation.
As you mentioned, I'm the first
generation daughter of
immigrants born and raised
right here in san francisco.
My parents are here today.
They built our business with
nothing but grit
and determination.
We had one client my uncle
and they called called out of
the yellow pages seven days a
week when I was a child to
build our business.
>> so everything that I am
today, every opportunity I've
had in this life has been the
product of two things their
sacrifices and being born here
in san francisco in this great
city san francisco is more than
my hometown growing up here
where the anti-war movement
civil rights movement, lgbtq
movement took root, I was
shaped by that energy and by
the belief that regular people
organizing together can change
the world.
That's what led me to to join
the foreign service and do
diplomatic work during the
obama administration and to
live a life of service here
in san francisco which I
believe is the vanguard of
progressive policies especially
as the rest of our country is
teetering toward fascism.
So thank you all for your
service and for showing the
world that di doesn't need to
be a dirty word that san
francisco is the best city
in this country and that we can
lead the way again and on
behalf of the next generation
of san franciscans of kids,
immigrant kids, working class
kids who deserve to see
themselves in every war room
where decisions are made.
I accept this commendation on
behalf of them and on behalf of
my parents.
So thank you for this
recognition and for believing
in a san francisco that belongs
to all of us going so you can
go or not go there.
Thank you.
That's great.
I think that was sweet but long
MADAME Clerk I think we can
finally get to our 3 P.M.
Special orders and I would ask
that we deal with items 22
through 29 first I'll begin
with items 22 through 25.
This is a public hearing of
persons interested in the
determination of exemption from
environmental review under the
california environmental
quality act issued as a
categorical exemption by the
planning department on APRIL
5th, 2020 for for the proposed
project for 1310 junipero serra
boulevard which proposes the
demolition of nine maintenance
and facility structures
and construction of a 25 foot
tall one story maintenance
building approximately 20,000
gross square feet in size.
Item 23 is the motion to affirm
the department's determination
the planning department's
determination that this project
is categorically exempt from
environmental review.
Item 24 reverses that decision.
Item 25 is the motion to direct
the preparation of findings
items 26 through 30.
This is the public hearing of
persons interested in the
approval of a conditional use
authorization for this 1310
junipero serra boulevard
project which would allow the
construction of a 19,100 gross
square foot one storey
accessory maintenance
and facility building for an
existing open area recreation
area use dba item 27 is the
motion to approve the decision
of the planning commission for
this project and making the
environmental findings item 28
is the motion that disapproves
the planning department's
decision of for this
conditional use authorization.
Item 29 is the motion to direct
the preparation of findings.
>> all right.
Thank you, MADAM Clerk.
>> so we have these two appeal
hearings before us.
>> colleagues with two
appellants on the proposed
project at 1301 justin pair of
sara boulevard items as our
clerk indicated item 2325
comprised the appeal the
determination of exemption from
environmental review and items
26 to 29 are the appeal of the
conditional use authorizations.
It is my impression
understanding that agreements
have been reached and I'm
wondering supervisor melgar, if
you want to say anything at
this point?
>> yes.
Yes.
Thank you very much PRESIDENT
Randleman and thank you
colleagues for your patience
and understanding as we got to
a place with a path forward
that is you know, acceptable to
both parties and if I also want
to just thank profusely mike
parra on my staff who worked
for months to get us to this
place and to all the parties
for their goodwill and try to
work it out.
>> so if I could ask MR.
Patterson to please come up
and explain what where we've
reached.
>> thank you.
Thank you very much supervisor
melgar, PRESIDENT Madeline
and other supervisors ryan
patterson of patterson
and o'neill, attorney for linda
shaw of the friends of st
thomas more I was brought
in recently to help move the
parties toward an agreement
and very happy to report that
we have reached an agreement
and a big thanks to staff as
noted for really going the
extra mile on this really above
and beyond we've reached an
agreement between the parties
that provides significant
protections for st thomas more
school next door these safety
measures include dealing with
construction traffic, chemical
and fuel storage, tree removal,
dust controls and particulate
monitoring, automatic alarms to
alert the school of emergencies
wall strengthening water runoff
controls and significantly an
enhanced fire suppression
system for lithium ion
batteries.
Several of these terms we are
requesting to be incorporated
as conditions of approval
and that's that's basically it
very pleased with the outcome
and big thanks to everyone who
helped with this.
I'll turn it over to john kevin
representing the san francisco
golf club in case he has
anything to add.
>> thank you.
Thank you, MR. Patterson.
>> thank you, supervisor john
kaplan here with robin jenison
rose on behalf of the san
francisco golf club.
We're also very happy to be
here today with an agreement
between the parties that makes
everyone comfortable moving
forward with this project.
And I would just confirm
everything ryan just said
and asked that the board please
affirm where we're at so we can
all move forward.
Thank you very much.
>> thank you MADAM Clerk.
I think we have to take public
comment at this point, correct?
Correct.
>> yes it might.
Mike on there we go.
So yes, we have apparently
agreements but we still need to
take public comment on these
matters with the understanding
the secret deal has been
withdrawn and we are going to
be making some modifications to
the conditional use.
I'm going to open up public
comment again on this on these
appeals.
>> MADAM Clerk, will you please
call the first speaker?
Sure.
Are there any members of the
public who would like to
address the board on this
appeal as well as the
conditional use appeal?
Right.
MR. PRESIDENT.
>> right.
It looks like not so I'm going
to close public comment
and seeing and hope well, I'm
going to I'm going to get rid
of the here at the hearings
first.
So before calling on supervisor
melgar items 22 and 26 have
been held and are now filed
and the supervisor melgar okay
well I'd like to make a motion
to approve item 23 and table
items 24 and 25.
>> great.
There is a motion from
supervisor melgar.
Is there a second a second
second supervisor walton
and that's so without objection
item 23 is approved items 24
and 25 are tabled.
>> okay.
Okay.
>> supervisor melgar.
Yes.
Thank you MR. PRESIDENT.
So I will like to make a motion
to amend item 28 to disapprove
the current condition of all
use authorization and approve a
revised conditional use
authorization with additional
conditions which I have shared
with all of you in hard copies
and it's also in your email
and I will read it into the
record as follows during the
construction of the projects
the project sponsor shall make
good faith efforts to route all
construction traffic on roads
other than st thomas more way
to conduct tree removal
activity either outside of the
typical instructional hours or
during the summer school recess
and three on days when
earthmoving activities taking
place apply water to portions
of the site where such
activities are taking place at
least three times during
construction of the project.
The project sponsor shall
comply with all applicable
provisions of health code
related to dust control,
establish and publish sites via
onsite posting a phone hotline
for reports of fugitive dust
develop a response plan to
address any construction
related emergencies or
unanticipated discharges.
A fugitive dust and then during
construction of in review of
construction drawings for the
project the project sponsor
shall comply with any
requirements imposed by the
department of building
inspection in the fire
department as especially as
they relate to fire prevention
and suppression comply with any
requirements imposed by the san
francisco public utilities
commission regardless regarding
some stormwater control
and design and install an alarm
along the northern elevation of
the proposed building that
provides audio and visual
warnings that a smoke or fire
alarm in the proposed building
has been activated.
Thank you all.
Thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
And in addition to that I would
like to make a motion to
approve item 28 as amended
approve item 29 and table item
27.
Okay so we have two motions.
Thank you supervisor melgar to
you and your staff for working
diligently to work this out for
us without us having to
struggle too terribly much here
at the board is let's take them
each in turn so the motion to
amend item 28 as described by
supervisor melgar is there a
second for that's seconded by
mahmood and I think we can take
that amendment without
objection.
>> without objection the
amendments are approved.
>> and then uh, supervisor
melgar, you made a second
motion to approve item 28 as
amended and item 29 and to
table item 27 I believe.
And is there a second for that?
Also seconded by mahmud.
>> MADAM Clerk, will you please
call the roll on that motion?
The motion to table item 27
approve item 28 as amended
and 29 supervisor mahmood
mahmood I supervisor randleman
I randleman I supervisor melgar
I melgar I supervisor sadr
sutter I supervisor cheryl
cheryl I supervisor walton
walton eyes supervisor chan
chin eyes supervisor chin chin
eyes supervisor dorsey dorsey I
supervisor and gaudio
and gaudio I and supervisor
fielder fielder either are
lebanese thank you MADAM Clerk
without objection items to
eight as amended and 29 are
approved and item 27 is tabled
.
>> okay MADAM Clerk let's go to
our other 3 P.M. Special order
items 20 and 21 yes.
>> item 20 is a public hearing
to consider objections to a
report of delinquent charges
for code enforcement cases with
delinquent assessment of costs
and fees pursuant to the
provisions of the building code
submitted by the director of
the department of building
inspection for services
rendered by said department of
costs thereof having accrued
pursuant to the building code
enforcement violations item 21
this is the resolution to
approve a report of delinquent
charges for assessment costs
submitted by the director of
the department of building
inspection for the delinquent
charges for code enforcement
violations and associated fees.
>> all right, colleagues.
So as described we have a
hearing before us on the report
of assessment costs for
building code enforcement
violations.
>> I believe it was just a
gavel that and the first we
hear from tbi.
Thank you, PRESIDENT Benjamin,
members of the board.
Good afternoon and I'm senior
housing inspector matt luton.
This is the 28th year the
department of building
inspection is before this board
requests the imposition of a
special assessment leans on
properties for code enforcement
cases previously transmitted to
you is the report of delinquent
charges dated APRIL 21st 2025
prior to today's hearing I
notice the listed property
owners on two separate
occasions and held two in-house
hearings for owners to discuss
their outstanding fees.
The department appreciates your
support in approving the report
of delinquent charges.
>> this is a very important
and useful tool for cost
recovery for time spent.
>> thank you and thank you to
the clerk of the board and her
staff.
Thank you.
>> thank you for your
presentation.
Supervisor chan a person
management I know I just want
to say I know that we the owner
on the list for 5 to 2 34th
avenue has actually pay the
fine this morning so I just
wanted to see if we can strike
out that address but of course
with the confirmation that the
owner did pay and if the you
know if I can affirm but I'm
just put it out there the
address is 522 34th avenue
52252 we're looking at the
wrong one is it line ten
supervisor chen which yes thank
you.
It has been removed.
It is currently in red.
Thank you.
All right.
So we are going to open this up
for public comment but I
understand that we have
and specifically that alan
davidson as he has on many
occasions before helped us
resolve a number of these
issues.
>> I did want to invite MR.
Davidson to come up to receive
our abundant thanks for his
efforts not just today but on
prior occasions.
I have not had the privilege or
honor of getting to know you
but our clerk raves about you
and says you are amazing
and said MR. PRESIDENT, you
must bring him up and give him
some accolades.
So I'm doing the best I can to
honor you appropriately but let
us know what happened.
>> it's much appreciated
and it's been coming up on 31
years now and it's been a
pleasure.
I love being a health
inspector.
I love being a senior housing
inspector as as middle
management and my job has
always been to keep it at my
level and below.
I love you know, being a native
san franciscan.
I love working with people of
san francisco from all walks of
life.
>> it's been a pleasure.
It's bittersweet but I think
I'm ready to volunteer at the
spca.
>> I think I think that's my
next venture and just doing
things I want to do but it's
it's been a pleasure working
with everybody here.
I've known angela for so long
mary as well.
We go way back to the sro task
force meetings right down the
hall here so I really
appreciate you honoring me
and giving me the opportunity
to come up and speak.
>> there are also a couple of
properties that were coming
off.
I just want to make sure we got
them because I've just speaking
with them in the office if
you'd like me to read them on
the record now I can that would
be great.
>> okay so what they were it
was 15 noble which was item
number at the time 28 and 29.
>> okay.
And the last two were items 56
and 57 146 vernon MR.
PRESIDENT, if I could also add
to the members if you could
take a look at them standard of
the list that's in front of
you.
This is the model that we use
with other departments.
So we are grateful to alan
and his colleagues for always
making the list so clear for us
to be able to review addresses.
>> it's been a work in progress
.
>> we have a creature that is
afraid of change according to
certain people but there's also
a few more.
There was a line item number
six which is 14, 15, 23rd line
item number 45 and 46 which is
250 silver and you're still
going to see me because I still
live in the city but I have a
great afternoon.
>> thank you so much, MR.
Davidson okay.
>> so it sounds like great work
has already happened this
afternoon but I do want to open
this item up for public comment
again just some items 20 and 21
so if you're here to speak on
items 20 or 21 please come to
the podium if you're here today
but don't want to provide
public testimony we still
you've sold me how you still
have we'll have the opportunity
to speak with department staff
if you haven't already and just
indicate that we want or need
to do that outside chambers
and public comment is now open
and you're welcome to speak.
>> good afternoon PRESIDENT
Mandolin members of the board.
My name is emily breath and my
office represents rafael
garcia, the owner of 1465
oakdale avenue which is listed
on the report as items 30
and 31 and being subject to two
separate delinquent assessments
.
My client objects to the
assessments being confirmed by
the board today as these
assessments are also the
subject of a pending court
enforcement action by the city
against my client and which the
city in my client are currently
in negotiations to resolve my
client who is originally from
mexico and does not speak
english is also in the midst of
trying to resolve a number of
property violations at the
oakdale property with the
assistance of his daughter he's
been working diligently with
the planning department
and like I said in addition
discussing settlement with the
city to resolve this global
matter as such my client
respectfully requests that the
board strike or stay or
otherwise modify the report's
assessments on oakdale avenue.
>> for these reasons they are
already being dealt with
another venue the superior
court and I do have a copy of
the pending court case here as
well as the notice of this
hearing that was sent to my
client with the violations at
issue highlighted in both
documents to show that they are
the same violations at issue if
the board is interested
in seeing those, is there
anyone else who'd like to speak
?
Is that a question about this
supervisor walton or okay.
All right.
Let's see if there's any
further public comment on item
20 or 21 seeing so any other
members of the public would
like to speak on the assessment
costs for building code
enforcement violations?
>> I don't see anyone so I'm
going to close public comment
and supervisor walton thank you
PRESIDENT Amendment a question
about what public commenters
say it does.
Do we have the same information
or no to this is to divide this
debate.
I have the same belief or no
I'm not aware of that specific
case.
I haven't we haven't spoken yet
about this case so I don't know
how we can allow the time for
them to have that come.
>> thank you.
Supervisor walton all right.
I probably should have after
it.
Well, let's see.
I'm going to close the public
hearing item 20 and then we do
have a little bit of time left
in this meeting at least public
comments worth.
So I'm going to invite tbi
staff to speak with counsel for
this property and get any
advice that we MAY need from
our city attorney and maybe
we'll come back to this after
public after general public
comment.
All right.
So we'll come back to that
later in the meeting and I
think that take MADAM Clerk we
go back to roll call.
>> yes.
Thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
Supervisor melgar your next up
to introduce new business.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
>> so first I will give an
update on my outside boards
and commission.
I sit on the metropolitan
transportation commission and a
of the committees under that so
of note at the commission this
month passed resolutions
supporting the extension of the
state's cap and trade program
the affordable housing bond act
of 2026 and of course support
for sb 63 which is senator
wiener in oregon's bill
enabling a regional measure to
support public transit in the
bay area and then for both our
which is the joint air bag
and mtc oversight committee of
the bay area housing finance
authority, we approved the
strategic plan for the agency
which includes a plan to put
forward a regional housing bond
again to try again in the
future to provide financing for
regional affordable housing
production in work with
stakeholders and bay area
counties to plan and align the
goals with all of our
respective housing elements
in the work that each county is
doing at both our right now has
an outstanding request to the
governor for $30 million for
the agency for this year for
which they're requesting all of
our support which includes some
operating funds for the agency
and for its programs including
the small site acquisition work
that they have been doing very
successfully throughout the bay
area.
>> colleagues today at work
yesterday at the ladies
and transportation committee we
had a very insightful hearing
on street safety and economic
recovery.
The hearing was inspired by a
budget in legislative analyst
report that demonstrated that
traffic crashes have cost san
franciscans $2.5 billion over
the last five years.
That's health insurance
payouts, car insurance payouts,
lost productivity, property
damage and more.
And it's paid by drivers,
transit riders, pedestrians
and bicyclists.
>> my colleague supervisor chen
and supervisor mahmud and I
heard from the department of
public health, the mta, the
police department and others
about how we have pursued our
vision zero goals over the past
few years and how we can
and must do better going
forward to save lives and save
money.
That is why today I am
initiating a drafting a request
for vision 02.0 policy carrying
us forward for the next ten
years.
Fixing this problem will not
take just one department, just
one neighborhood or just one
hearing.
It will take collaboration
between departments and they
will take buy in from all of
our district supervisors and it
will encourage and it will take
courage for us to break up the
status quo.
Additionally, as I discussed
last week in collaboration with
the planning department, I am
calling for a hearing at the
latest in transportation
committee to provide members of
the public and this board
another opportunity to discuss
the complex policy
considerations including but
not limited to ten protections
small business support
and affordability requirements
for housing as it pertains to
the rezoning plan for to comply
with our housing element
and state requirements, this
will provide another touch
point before the legislative
package makes its way to the
board of supervisors in the
fall with presentations by the
planning department and the
mayor's office and I look
forward to the robust
discussion and to everyone
participate who wants the rest
I submit.
Thank you.
Supervisor melgar.
>> supervisor sauder thank you
colleagues along alongside many
of you I just stood
in chinatown surrounded by our
small business community to
announce and applaud
significant small business
reform in the permit S.F.
Package thanks to the
leadership of mayor lurie, our
office of small business
and the planning department we
are getting serious about
supporting small businesses
in our city by removing
outdated rules and slashing
unnecessary regulation in one
piece of legislation that I'm
proud to sponsor we will allow
more uses on the ground floor
downtown.
And another example will
simplify business sign
requirements and remove permits
and fees for many of them
and in legislation that will
really help chinatown we will
expand an amnesty program to
now include security gates
in projecting signs and have a
streamlined process for their
approval.
I hope that we will work
quickly to pass these important
pieces of legislation as they
are heard and make it easier
for small businesses in our
city to start, grow and sustain
themselves.
Today I'm also requesting the
issuance of a letter of inquiry
to the city administrator
regarding the 311 api.
>> I was concerned to recently
learn that the 311 api will be
shutting down effective JULY
12th since its launch in 2010.
>> the promise of san
francisco's 311 api has been to
invite residents to build
technology in tandem with our
city to help solve civic
problems and that is exactly
what we've seen a baby resident
created air bits a system that
uses drones to quickly identify
hotspots for illegal trash
dumping.
A mission resident created
solve S.F. A innovative app
that allows residents to take a
photo and use ai to identify
the issue.
A resident created safe lanes
which is documented thousands
of incidents of vehicles
illegally parked in bus
and bike lanes.
But now all of these services
and the thousands of san
francisco residents who rely on
them for rely on using them for
cleaner and safer streets MAY
face an uncertain future.
>> my letter of inquiry
outlines approximately a dozen
questions that I hope will
bring clarity to this situation
quickly as a city we should
invite civic participation,
promote open government
and collaboration with the tech
sector.
>> I look forward to working
with the three on one team
in the office of city
administrator to ensure we can
continue to do just this with a
functioning 311 api and the
rest I submit.
>> thank you supervisor sartor
supervisor cheryl colleagues
I'd like to adjourn today's
meeting and member in memory of
peter john flannery a cherished
san franciscan and longtime
co-owner of brian's market
whose presence shaped the heart
of lower laurel village and our
city.
Peter passed away on APRIL
13th, 2025 at 81 surrounded by
family in mill valley.
He was born on AUGUST 24th,
1943 to mary and brian flannery
just minutes after his twin
sister nancy.
He grew up in san francisco
attending st agnes saint
brendan said ignatius and the
university of san francisco
while still in high school he
began working with his father
at the grant market and later
helping open brian quality
brian's quality meats in laurel
village in 1963.
Relocating the shop in 1993
and expanding it in 1998 for
six decades peter helped shape
brian's into a neighborhood
institution known for its high
quality meats friendly service
and personal touch with his
pets, dress shirts, v-neck
sweaters and ever present
tassel loafers.
>> peter brought warmth
and grace to the grocery
business.
Brian's market was closed only
on sundays so peter and his
brother terry could attend mass
and open the other six days to
generations of loyal customers
who became more like family.
Peter led by example, never
confining himself to the
office.
He stocked shelves cut meat
and greeted patrons by name
often with a dry sense of humor
and a quiet smile.
He and his wife of 56 years lou
del raised their daughters
meehan and petra with the same
humility, faith and generosity
he brought to every part of his
life.
He was a devoted grandfather to
quinn and peter and a steadfast
brother to brian terry nancy
and mary.
Peter helped neighborhood kids
find their first summer jobs
quietly supported charitable
causes like ucsf's care center
and made donations without ever
expecting anything in return.
He believed in showing up,
doing the work and treating
people with dignity.
These values he lived by even
while quietly battling cancer,
often driving himself to chemo
after a full day at the store.
His steady presence attention
to detail and quiet leadership
will be missed deeply not just
by his family and employees but
by the many customers
and neighbors like my family
who felt they belonged at
brian's because of him.
>> on behalf of the board of
supervisors as of my family, of
my neighbors we extend our
deepest condolences to the
flanary family, the brian's
marquette community and all who
mourn peter's passing.
MAY his memory continue to
inspire the grace, integrity
and neighborhood spirit that
defined peter's life.
>> the rest of us submit.
Thank you.
Supervisor sheryl supervisor
walton.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Colleagues today I'll be
introducing a resolution
opposing the governor's
proposed medi-cal cuts for
undocumented adults
and reaffirming san francisco's
commitment to immigrant health.
These cuts would freeze new
enrollment in 2026 and pose
$100 a month premium
and eliminate critical benefits
like long term care and dental
.
>> they are unjust, fiscally
shortsighted and will not solve
the budget deficit.
Instead they push people into
emergency rooms, shift costs to
local governments and threaten
the public health progress
we've made.
We must stand with our
immigrant communities to help
to protect access to care.
As far as external boards i
have a few updates.
The juvenile justice
coordinating council on APRIL
15th the jcc approved this
annual plan which outlines
strategic priorities
and funding allocations for
juvenile justice programs
in the upcoming year for a work
force investment san francisco
our workforce investment board
at our last meeting or iwd
shared updates on economic
recovery and budget challenges
including a projected shortfall
of up to 1 billion and reduced
general fund allocations.
Iwd is pursuing regional
planning efforts leveraging
state grants like california
jobs first and conducting a
citywide evaluation of
workforce programs.
They also acknowledge concerns
about federal employee layoffs
and is working with edi to
better track and support
affected workers.
Bay area air quality management
district which is now really
changed.
Too bad the bay area air
district despite receiving only
1.6% of its funding from
federal resources its programs
remain fully supported through
a diverse range of funding
and regulations are fully
enforceable under state law.
Earlier this month over $3
million and james carrie smith
community grants was awarded to
12 nonprofit organizations
including organizations in san
francisco.
Additionally, the 2025 charge
program is offering $10 million
in funding to support the
installation of electric
vehicle chargers with the focus
on multifamily housing
and projects located
in underserved areas.
The district is also seeking
new members for its community
advisory council and caltrain
joint powers board.
Caltrain experienced nearly 60%
year over year ridership growth
between APRIL 24th and APRIL
25th with total monthly
ridership reaching
approximately 925,000 in APRIL.
Weekend ridership hit record
highs though overall numbers
remain at 56% of 2019 levels.
When farebox recovery nearly
was nearly 75% of operational
costs to improve customer
experience, caltrain has
implemented a range of
enhancements including
increased train frequency,
improve wi-fi service,
personalized alerts, station
repairs, new visual display
signage and installation of 30
bicycle lockers.
New fare initiatives such as
the dollar youth fare of dirigo
pass and pass for programs have
also been rolled out
in response to financial
challenges.
Caltrain has lost an internal
cost reduction and efficiency
program.
This includes a hiring freeze
for new full time employees a
strategic freeze on select
vacancies and improved crew
scheduling practices.
Caltrain is also working with
legislators and partners to
receive energy credits for
regenerative braking which
allows up to 25% of energy to
be returned to the grid for
safety.
Caltrain has begun deploying ai
powered rail sentry technology
using cameras and light addr to
monitor vehicle and crossing
patterns at two crossings with
more installation planned
and last additional quick build
safety improvements such as
fencing channels station
and barriers are also being
implemented.
>> the rest I submit.
Thank you.
Supervisor walton.
>> supervisor chen thank you
MADAM Clerk.
>> I will be submitting
legislation but I just want to
quickly report back my also our
cyber assignment mainly the
free city college oversight
committee.
On friday MAY 2nd the committee
the oversight committee has
make a series of motion to
recommend really on the fees
city college mou to the city
for the city to consider mainly
really is for the city to
consider potentially fee for
additional in and indirect
expenses from the prior fiscal
years before the 2025 2026 only
upon the completion of the
audits of fiscal years 2223
and 2324.
>> with that though, it's also
another motion for the city to
consider meeting the existing
mou obligation of $16.4 million
for the fiscal year 2526
and compounded cpi for the
coming years.
In addition for the city to
consider increase of the mou
obligation based on the
recommendation provided by
students proposal and the
oversights committee when the
city is no longer in budget
deficit for the also for the
city to consider to strike out
the existing clause in the mou
regarding the reduction of
funding and replace a language
consistent with a deficit
trigger language when it comes
to reduction of fun and another
motion is for the city to
consider reimburse students
fees and tuition both
retroactively and moving
forward to include but not
limited ongoing student debt
fee covering health care web
registrations, student
representation and then last
but not least is also a motion
for the city to consider all
and all entities involved
in the implementation of the
mou to evaluate and amend the
language in the section of use
of fun and adjustments
and change in the mou.
>> all this is in the goal.
I really hope that we can
continue to sustain free city
college which is a program
in city college of san
francisco allowing residents of
san francisco and residents of
san francisco be able to have
higher education for free.
And it's a really important
program that has been really
for the past generations the
san franciscans.
But I really believe for the
future generations of san
franciscans as well not to only
to have higher education but to
have workforce development
and training and the rest I
submit.
>> thank you.
Supervisor chan supervisor chen
submit thank you.
>> supervisor dorsey thank you,
MADAM Clerk colleagues I'll
start with my updates from
outside boards as you MAY
recall I serve as your
appointee to the health service
board where we recently
welcomed reagan to the role of
executive director of san
francisco's health service
system.
Ray previously served as the
chief operating officer for hhs
and served as the interim
director after director
ambiance retirement.
Ray bring ray brings more than
two decades of experience
in employee benefits
administration to serving
in similar roles for san mateo
and santa clara counties for
the last three years he served
as the chief operating officer
at a process where he led the
team through pandemic recovery
and restored in-person support
for our members.
The board's process considered
many excellent candidates for
that role and ray was an
excellent choice and the top
pick I look forward to working
with ray and everyone on his
team as I continued my service
on the health service board.
I also now sit as the board's
representative on the bay
conservation and development
commission dc and I attended my
first two meetings this month
at our MAY 1st meeting we
approved the final emr iir for
cargill's solar salt system a
process that has taken five
years.
At that meeting we also
approved an update to the san
francisco bay climate change
policy guidance document at our
MAY 15th meeting.
We also approved the
application for phase three of
the india basin shoreline park.
So congratulations to
supervisor walton on an
exciting project moving forward
in his his district and thank
you to our own recreation
and parks department for their
efforts on that.
We also received a briefing on
proposed updates to streamline
bccdc permitting regulatory
regulations.
I look forward to the work
ahead to approve and implement
those improvements in APRIL
and MAY I attended the first
meetings that during my since
my appointment to bag the
association four bay area
governments we took action to
support two state bills one
from assembly member buffy
wicks which adds housing
support services as a new
medi-cal benefit for enrollees
and another from assembly
member dave cortez to create a
multifamily housing loan,
insurance and credit
enhancement program backed by
the state's credit rating.
We also enacted relatively
minor bylaws changes governing
elections procedures the big
governor general assembly is
coming up in JUNE and their
democrat delegates will review
and approve the 2526 a bag
budget and work program
and hear from a panel of
elected officials and other
leaders regarding examples of
how regional tools
and technical assistance have
benefited their communities.
Next, an item I'm introducing
today colleagues I'm today
submitting a letter of inquiry
to two of the city departments
tasked by mayor daniel lurie
with implementing behavioral
health innovations to consider
the embarcadero navigation
center for a near-term
conversion to a drug free
recovery oriented pilot program
for homeless adults in san
francisco.
My letter of inquiry asks san
francisco's department of
public health and department of
homelessness and supportive
housing to estimate the
resources, staffing and time
necessary to convert the 200
bed congregate shelter into a
drug free recovery focused
pilot which MAY be based on the
restore model or similar
program that allows medication
assisted treatment requires
periodic drug testing
and prohibits the use of
illicit drugs while residing
there.
As some of us MAY have seen
in recent news reports last
month, restore is an acronym
for rapid engagement shelter
and treatment for opioid
recovery.
And mayor leary's
administration announced a
successful implementation of
that strategy as a drug free
recovery oriented approach
in non congregate homeless
shelter settings.
Last month at a moment when san
francisco was beginning to see
real progress in supporting
long term recovery for those on
our streets who struggle with
deadly drug addictions now is
the time to double down on an
approach that is working and to
explore expanding this model to
a navigation center.
Moreover, given this facility's
proximity right next door to
the delancey street foundation,
one of the nation's leading
residential self-help recovery
institutions which has
expressed an openness to
explore ways that it might help
support a drug free
and recovery oriented pilot
program.
The embarcadero navigation
center is uniquely positioned
for success in ways that few
other city facilities could
match.
I really want to applaud
mayor larry for his efforts to
put long term recovery at the
forefront of his
administration's response to
our drug crisis.
I very much appreciate my
colleagues support for the
recovery.
First ordinance we finally
passed last week which is on
mayor larry's desk at this
moment I believe and I look
forward to making progress on
our recovery first approach
and learning more about what a
drug free recovery focused
embarcadero navigation center
might entail to better serve
those san franciscans who are
both unsheltered and seeking
long term recovery from
addictions to live a healthy
life free from illicit drug use
and the rest I submit.
>> thank you.
Supervisor dorsey supervisor as
you're injured you submit.
Thank you.
Supervisor fielder thank you,
MADAM Clerk.
>> colleagues today I'm
introducing a performance audit
of the recreation and parks
department by budget
and legislative analysts.
>> the function of regular
performance audits is to ensure
that city departments
and agencies make prudent
and efficient use of city
resources and also effectively
perform the functions assigned
to them by the charter
and applicable laws.
>> recreation and parks
department has not undergone a
department wide performance
audit in over ten years.
>> this audit is particularly
timely given reports of a lack
of oversight on donations to
the parks alliance made from
individuals and organizations
that do direct business with
the recreation and parks
department.
>> it is my hope that greater
transparency will result
in better outcomes for all san
franciscans.
My commitment is to ensure that
san franciscans have a
government that they can trust
to provide equitable access to
basic services and green spaces
and to ensure that our city's
public resources are equitably
allocated to san franciscans
across the city and not just
this one the ones who live
downtown or in traditionally
well-served neighborhoods.
I would like to thank
supervisor walton supervisor
chen for co-sponsoring this
motion.
Russ I submit thank you
supervisor fielder and MR.
PRESIDENT, seeing no names on
the roster or no requests to re
refer.
That concludes the introduction
of new business.
>> all right.
Thank you, MADAM Clerk.
let's go to public comment at
this time the board welcomes
your general public comment.
Please line up on your right
hand side of the chamber.
You MAY speak to the approval
of the board meeting minutes
and other general matters that
are not on today's agenda nor
you cannot speak to any of
these special order 3 P.M.
Hearings that we have held thus
far.
We are setting the timer for
two minutes.
MR. Washington let's let's hear
your comments please.
>> so before you started this
morning see and mom a
presentation of these
historical value.
First of all, you know I love
supervisors.
I've been through eight
administrations, eight mayors
cycles.
I go back when supervisors were
elected generally.
So I go back.
So what I have to say today is
so very important if not
pointed at anyone but I'm going
to say some things this year
the juneteenth was bid it out
rfp went held equal an rfp are
juneteenth our culture why are
they doing who well the
mayor and I hear that rfp the
valley brown put out an rfp
your probably don't know about
it but I am sick and tired.
I have to look in the papers
about what's happening.
It MAY MAY go just a minute but
please let me say I'm sick
and tired of this city on this
particular juneteenth in our
business, in our historical
black business why is the city
rfp and in in tears they gave a
dime out to the juneteenth yet
they going to do it in a couple
of days but the juneteenth is
less than a month away so what
they do and trying to make it
fail I'm appalled and this this
and I'm just so tired of this
and I only got a couple of
minutes but if you could shine
down on your own thing here the
juneteenth has been going on
for 80 years.
>> it started out with wesley
johnson right there.
So what I'm saying is somebody
the mayor hrc did the rfp.
>> they said we call that rfp.
Now the black community is
in uproar.
We don't have a dime.
We got to wait for the city to
pay us money when actually we
did it in the years we used to
get the money from the
community and corporations we
don't need no rfp.
My name is jason.
>> I'm not much time.
I can't say no more.
Thank you, MR. Washington.
All right.
Let's welcome our next speaker
.
>> hello, my name is leah
mckeever.
>> I live in dc six.
I made a comment at the board
of supervisors inaugural
meeting this year that I didn't
think the PRESIDENT Of the
board was serious about
protecting trans people because
of his yes vote on the gift
program settlement.
>> five of the 11 of you voted
in favor of the judicial watch
settlements.
Probably all of you voted yes
for the first one.
I didn't check a former trans
latina gift recipient has
reached out to me since then
out of a pool of ten former
trans latina recipients.
This is the results of your
actions board of supervisors
for these undocumented trans
latinas they don't have access
to social security or to
domestic violence is a problem
for nine out of ten of them
they're currently being abused
mental health issues have been
exacerbated by extreme poverty,
anxiety, ptsd all of them have
been forced to return to
survival.
>> prostitution including the
elders in their 60s and older.
>> the clients are more violent
post 2024 presidential election
,ten out of ten trans teens
are forced to do this.
>> some are hiv positive
currently still have access to
medication.
Are you going to guarantee
access to their medication?
>> MAY I remind you of what you
said during commendations today
when you center the most
vulnerable among us, you create
a future where everyone
thrives.
What are you going to do to
right this wrong?
>> you did.
This is from the former gift
recipient the gift program
which was implemented in an
effort to provide these women
with minimal financial support
was beginning to offer an
alternative to prostitution
and precarious living.
However, with the programs
elimination the situation has
worsened significantly.
The girls no longer have the
financial security the program
once provided and now more than
ever the cycle of poverty
and abuse has intensified.
It's important to recognize
that the city of san francisco
owes our trans latino community
reparations for historical harm
.
>> the discrimination we have
suffered over the years has
been systematic and cannot
continue to be ignored.
>> are you going to hold
yourselves accountable
especially the ones who voted
yes for this?
>> thank you for your comments.
Let's welcome our next speaker
.
Hi.
Good evening, angela.
Long time no see and very
toronto present amount of men
and fellow supervisors.
I first want to say that I try
to reach out to a supervisor
and her staff regarding the
waymo issue.
Market street got no response
and so I'm wondering if there's
another supervisor can work
with a group of us regarding
this issue because once you
that waymo on to market street
you're opening the floodgates
you're hurting public transit
on market street you're making
it more dangerous for
bicyclists, a bit strange
and you're making it more
difficult for taxi drivers who
serve seniors and disabled to
do their job on market street.
So I appreciate it.
You have a hearing and hear a
hearing on this and a committee
or at least pass a resolution
and opposing this this mayor's
idiotic record decision.
It's not kind of farewell for
anybody.
So the clock hasn't started
yet.
So so anyway, I would
appreciate if if if you could
take this more seriously
because it has brought a
coalition of unlikely folks
together taxi drivers,
bicyclists, pedestrians,
transit riders, activists to to
fight this this this idiotic
decision to allow waymo into
market street for many reasons
they MAY be safe vehicles but
they're not safe for other
users of the road.
So I appreciate it that you
take this more seriously really
would be helpful.
The next thing is that castro
street having been a busy area
for taxi usage has become a
mess.
Dangerous not just not just for
the double parked cars but
because there are a lot of
riffraff on the street that
still exist even with more
police presence and and and and
we've got to support castro
street but the castro theater
being closed still and for
months and months created
problems and please sign the
petition to keep the nail shop
and the coffee shop open
because because they have
really done a disservice to the
community by by not having open
yet and ruined a lot of the the
about the film festivals that
rely on that space to to bring
a lot of people out and to keep
the businesses running smoothly
and to make and make the
businesses have more success so
it has been a problem so I
would appreciate it you look
into this and also look into
the issue of the lack of
enforcement at night of all the
double parked vehicles that are
hurting muni to get to run more
efficiently.
>> thank you for your time.
>> thank you for your comments.
Welcome to our next speaker.
Are there any other members of
the public who would like to
address the board during
general public comment?
Please line up.
Welcome.
>> hi.
GOD it's a nerve wracking oh I
wasn't you guys wasn't supposed
to hear that on the mike.
>> I've stood out in dc board
of director of higher education
district ten representing
and I'm just addressed it
in about the supervisor
and spoke about higher
education.
I heard from a reliable source
that the mayor buzz's proposal
is coming soon and we hope that
this leaf city college will be
fully funded, continue to be
fully funded due to the fact
that we all know what's going
on outside his bubble in san
francisco.
But we want to make sure that
the money that will come to
city city college students
because this is like if we have
this free tuition you know, san
francisco for san francisco
students for all mean it will
also as well is their
investment I mean for the
economy because if if you don't
have to pay for tuition the
money can go into the small
business or the big businesses,
you know, go into that or
and also it also helps as
myself a middle class, you
know, person.
The city is very costly.
You make over 100 and you know,
$100,000.
>> it's a lot of money.
Like I said, it's very costly
but to it'll be a comfort those
who have free tuition so you
had to worry about that even
though we're we invested we
understand about paying our
taxes to help the less
fortunate which is great but
it'll be great for us not being
a catch 22.
So we be able to have some kind
of resources for us which is
heaven free tuition at city
college.
>> so that will help the middle
class and will help everyone
else for all I mean so please
reconsider that.
And the supervisor they spoke
about that.
>> I was hoping that I can talk
to her for five minutes, maybe
ten minutes.
No, no.
Like in an event or something
that we can talk about this
more to it.
>> thank you for your comments.
Thank you.
Welcome.
Our next speaker board
PRESIDENT Man, woman and board
members.
My name is richard peterson
and I will last meeting at the
end I tried to give a shout out
for our french frenchman who's
with a thick accent and a hair
coat and his name sounds like
theory phil but it's ted a fear
which is hard to pronounce.
>> but in any event, I wanted
to show another lack of
responsibility by our so-called
behind the scene leaders.
this is when I was still an
attorney and I signed it as an
attorney and it was just a
proposal.
It wasn't a summons and it gets
refused and return to sender
unable to forward all of these
leaders are ducking the
responsibility to respond to
the citizens.
>> I agree at my it was
probably stupid to put my name
as a as an attorney on that.
The other thing I wanted to
talk about quickly was the ted
fear.
>> I always railed against
artificial intelligence
and unfortunately the problems
that this city have won't be
solved without artificial
intelligence and I had to fill
out a form for my fortune
telling thing in hand they
don't even have automatic
filling of forms at the police
department.
This was a police department
issue and I certainly had
enough policemen here to try
and address that.
But anyway, I have a good
weekend.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Any other members of the public
like to address the board
during general public comment.
>> all right, MR. PRESIDENT,
all rights public comment is
now closed.
>> MADAM Clerk let's go to our
for adoption.
>> oh, before we do that, let's
bring 21 back right.
Thank you.
Senior housing inspector matt
luton.
We have decided to agree to
take off lines 30 and 31 from
the list for rate.
>> thank you.
Thank you.
All right.
So we now have an up dated
updated report on properties
based on the description that
we've gotten from my staff
colleagues can we accept the
amendments to the report that
we have heard described
and remove the properties?
I identified by department
staff?
>> let's do that without a
smoke.
>> without objection if there
are no objections we're going
to accept the changes and then
MADAM Clerk, can you please
call the roll on the resolution
with the amended report on item
21 with the amended report
supervisor mahmood mahmood I
supervisor randleman high medal
men I supervisor melgar melgar
I supervisor sadr sadr eyes
supervisor cheryl cheryl I
supervisor walton walton I
supervise her chin chin eyes
supervisor chin chin eyes
supervisor dorsey dorsey I
supervisor and engardio
and engardio I and supervisor
fielder fielder I there are 11
eyes without objection on item
21 is adopted with the amended
report MADAM Clerk can you take
us to the for adoption without
committee reference agenda
items 30 through 37 were
introduced for adoption but
without committee reference a
unanimous vote is required for
adoption of a resolution on
first reading alternative lee a
member MAY require a resolution
on first reading to go to
committee supervisor melgar I
don't want to sever anything
president I just want to be
added to the in memoriam for
alan martinez I'm so sorry I
when the roll call I forgot
thank you.
>> thank you supervisor dorsey
a 37 it's paul 37 and I
apologize folks I'm going to
ask to pull item 38 okay so on
the remaining balance of the
items MADAM Clerk can you call
the roll?
>> yes on items 36 and 38
supervisor mahmood mahmood I
supervisor randleman hi
gentlemen.
I'm supervisor melgar melgar I
supervisor sadr sadr I
supervisor cheryl cheryl I
supervisor walton walton I
supervisor chin chin I
supervisor dorsey dorsey I
supervisor engardio
and engardio I and supervisor
fielder fielder either ari
lebanese thank you MADAM Clerk
did we vote on 39 or no
and we'll call 39 separate or
will vote separately on 39 so
without objection the
resolutions are adopted that is
36 and 30.
>> oh wait a minute.
The member on maybe the reason
we voted on 36 and 39 36 I
don't think we wanted to vote
on three.
>> I okay MR. PRESIDENT okay.
>> I see I wrote down 36 and 38
moved to rescind the vote.
Thank you.
Thank you for that motion.
Do I need to second for that
matter I got a second from chan
will we will now I think we can
rescind the vote.
Same house, same call without
objection the the vote is
rescinded all right, madam
clerk, can you call the roll on
items 36 and 39 on items 36
and 39 supervisor mahmood
mahmood I supervisor randleman
hi melman I supervisor melgar
melgar I supervisor sadr sadr I
supervisor cheryl cheryl I
supervisor walton walton eyes
supervisor chan chin eyes
supervisor chin chin I
supervise her dorsey dorsey I
supervisor and engardio
in guardian I and supervisor
fielder fielder either ari
lebanese all right without
objection the resolution
and and motion a resolution is
adopted and the motion is
approved.
>> and thanks for the assist
supervisor walton MADAM Clerk,
can you please call item 37?
Item 37 this is a resolution to
commemorate bike to wherever
day on MAY 15th 2025 and to
celebrate san francisco's
commitment to sustainable
and active transportation
supervisor dorsey thank you
PRESIDENT Randleman I just
wanted to express my gratitude
to supervisor melgar for
introducing this resolution to
celebrate bike to wherever day
because I had back to back
meetings last thursday I was
unable to attend to any of this
year's events I did take to
social media however to note
that my I had a bike share ride
from city hall to my bcd
meeting downtown that completed
my 3,051st by bear wheels bike
share ride for a combined total
of 3615 bike share miles I
almost posted beat that
supervisor melgar and I'm glad
I didn't because when I texted
her about that she replied with
a shot of her bicycle odometer
reading 6960 miles so I am
proud to be one of the bike
iest supervisors even if I am a
distant second to supervisor
melgar supervisor sauder and I
bike to chinatown today so
perhaps he will give us a run
for our money but I'm just
appreciative to be part of a
board of supervisors that's not
just talking the talk but
biking the bike on bike to
wherever day thank you
supervisor dorsey I think then
we can take item 37 same house,
same call without objection the
resolution is adopted MADAM
Clerk please call item 38.
>> item 38 this is a resolution
to recognize the week of MAY
24th through JUNE 1st 2025 as
and transgender asian
and pacific islander week
in the city and county of san
francisco.
>> thank you MADAM Clerk and I
apologize.
Colleagues I would have spoken
about this last week but as you
know I wasn't here and so I did
want to call out this
resolution.
I love the fact that you topic
week and transgender asian
and pacific islander week
in san francisco falls right at
the end of apa heritage month
and right before the beginning
of pride.
I think that is lovely and is
one of the things I appreciated
about being able to sponsor
this resolution each year
and to remind everyone the the
bay area and transgender asian
and pacific islander coalition
was formed in 2019 to foster
community facilitate the
transfer of knowledge across
generations, recognize the
historical contributions
and interdependence of the
topic community and honor the
community's vibrant cultural
heritage and identity was first
recognized in san francisco
in 2020 one and then it
expanded to san diego, san
jose, oakland and alameda
in 2022 and the city of eugene,
oregon got in on the action
in 2023.
This year's key topics week
in san francisco will include
the first ever chinatown pride
procession the first ever q top
strong unity MARCH the closing
block party at the heart of the
castro and community engagement
events that will further the
work of the atopy movement
in san francisco and beyond.
I want to thank supervisors
chan chen dorsey melgar fielder
and guardiola sadr, mahmood
and walton for their
co-sponsorship of this
resolution and I also want to
thank michael wynn also known
as jesse lu, founder of the q
top coalition for working with
my office all these years on
this resolution.
And MADAM Clerk, I think that
we can muster objections.
Take this item same house, same
call the resolution is adopted
.
MADAM Clerk do we have any
imperative agenda items?
There are none, MR. PRESIDENT.
All right.
Can you please read the
in memoriam?
>> yesterday's meeting will be
adjourned in memory of the
following beloved individuals
on behalf of supervisor mandel
men and supervisor melgar for
the late former commissioner
alan wayne martinez and for on
behalf of supervisor cheryl for
the late MR. Peter flannery
and I think that brings us to
the end of our agenda MADAM
Clerk is there any further
business before us today?
>> I conclude o question about
the warrant what do we do about
21 we approved it.
We thank you.
>> yeah so I think we're I
think there's no further
business and I think we are
adjourned